<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Tarikh as-Sudân</title>
<author>Aberrahmen ben Abdallah ben 'Imran ben 'Amir es-Sa'di.</author>
<editor xml:lang="fra">O. Houdas</editor>
<funder>Volunteer</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>Editor-in-Chief, Perseus Digital Library</resp>
</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>

<idno type="filename">TBA.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2021</date>
<publisher>Perseus Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>

<title xml:lang="eng">Tarikh al-Fattâsh</title>
<editor>
<persName>
    <name xml:lang="fra">O. Houdas</name>
    <name xml:lang="eng">Gregory Crane</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:TBA">Mahmoûd Kâti et al.</author>

<imprint>
<publisher>Ernest Leroux</publisher>
<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
<date>1900</date>
</imprint>

<biblScope unit="pages">TBA</biblScope>

</monogr>
<ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=ien.35556012109526">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>


<encodingDesc>

<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards (January 2014)</p>
<p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE
Architecture.</p>


<refsDecl n="CTS">

<cRefPattern n="cited quotation" matchPattern="(.+).(.+).(.+)"
replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2']/tei:cit[@n='$3'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts single fragments</p>


</cRefPattern>

<cRefPattern n="paragraph" matchPattern="(.+).(.+)"
replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts all the fragments classified under the same paragraph number</p>
</cRefPattern>

<cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(.+)"
replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts books or sections</p>

</cRefPattern>




</refsDecl>

</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">English</language>
<language ident="grc">French</language>
<language ident="ara">Arabic</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="Gregory Crane">created the file</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body><pb n="103"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="131"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9"><head>CHAPTER IX (<foreign>rv</foreign>) BIOGRAPHY OF THE PRINCIPAL SAVANTS AND HOLY PEOPLE WHO HABITED TOMBOUCTOU AT VARIOUS TIMES (God have mercy on them, show them his satisfaction and let us benefit from their influence in this world and in the other!) MENTION OF THEIR MERITS AND THEIR WORKS.</head>

<p>On this subject it will suffice to reproduce what has been reported by trustworthy persons according to the master, the learned, the eminent, the holy personage, author of prodigies and miracles, the jurisconsult, the cadi Mohammed-El-Kabari (God have mercy on him!). This is what he said: "I have known saints from Sankore whose virtues have never been surpassed by anyone except the Companions of the Envoy of God (God shower his salvation and blessings on him and show them all his satisfaction!) Among these characters, we shall mention:</p>

<p>The jurisconsult El-Hâdj, grandfather of the cadi Abderrahman-ben-Abou-Bekr-ben-El-Hâdj. - He was invested with the functions of cadi of Timbuktu in the last years of the dynasty of the people of Melli. He was the first to order the reading of half a hizb of the Qur'an as a teaching<ref target="1"/>. This reading took place in the mosque of Sankore after the asr prayer and after the evening prayer. Together with his brother, the jurisconsult Ibrahim, he had come from Biro, and he settled in</p>

<note n="1">The hizb is one of the divisions of the Qur'an which has been divided into sixty sections bearing that name. I think that the purpose of reading or reciting these hizb was to teach the faithful the Qur'an; the text in this regard is not very specific.</p> <p>

<pb n="74"/>

<p>16 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>Benka<ref target="1"/>, where his tomb is located which is well known and visited on pilgrimage.</p>

<p>It is assured that he was a thaumaturgist, and our master, the eminent, the ascetic, the jurisconsult, El-Amin-ben-Ahmed, reported the following fact: It was in his time that the Sultan of Mossi made his expedition against Benka. The population of this locality went out to fight the enemy, and at that time a certain number of people were sitting near El-Hàdj. He said some words about millet and invited the people to eat it. All of them ate it except for one person, the son-in-law of El-Hajj, who did not dare to do so because of the ties of kinship that bound him to him. "Go now to battle," said the saint, "and you will have nothing to fear from the enemy's dashes." All, indeed, came back safe and sound, and only the person who had not eaten millet died in this fight. The Sultan of Mossi, routed, was driven out as well as his troops without having obtained the slightest advantage over the people of Benka and this thanks to the protection of this blessed holy personage.</p>.

<p>It was from this El-Hadj that the holy personage in God (<foreign>vw</foreign>), the jurisconsult Ibrahim, son of the holy jurisconsult, Cadi Omar dwelling in Yendibo'o<ref target="2"/> was descended. Both the father and the son were fervent worshippers of God.</p>.

<p>It was Askia-El-Hàdj-Mohammed who appointed 'Omar to the duties of cadi in that area. The latter had a nephew (son of his sister) who, from time to time, went on pilgrimages<ref target="3"/> to Timbuktu. The cadi of that city, the juriscon-</p>

<note n="1">Or: "Binga."</note>

<note n="2">Or again "Yendibogho", The ms. C spells Yendobo'o. We very often find the <foreign>g</foreign> in place of the <foreign>į</foreign> and vice versa.</note>

<note n="3">Or: "visit". The verb <foreign>olj</foreign> is most often used to indicate pious visits.</note>

<pb n="75"/>

<p>CHAPTER NINE</p>

<p>Sult Mahmud, came to complain to the Amir Askia-El-HâdjMohammed that this nephew was spying on what he said and then reporting it to the people of Yendibo'o. When the prince camped at Tila, Cadi Omar surrounded by the notables of the town of Yendiboʻo came to greet him. "Where is this nephew?" asked the prince. - Here he is," was the reply. - So," he added, "it is you who are reporting to your maternal uncle the words spoken by the jurisconsult Mahmud." On hearing this speech, the cadi 'Omar cried out in anger: "It is you who are the cause of all these intrigues, since you have appointed a cadi in Timbuktu and another in Yendibo'o!" Thereupon the cadi, highly irritated, headed for the port, saying to his companions: "Let's leave, let's cross the river and let's go! When the cadi arrived at the edge of the river, he was about to enter it when he was told: "The boat has not yet arrived, wait until it comes. - And if there was none?" he answered. His companions, understanding that he wanted to cross the River without waiting for the boat, held him back and made him sit down until the boat having arrived all together passed the River (God have mercy on them and make us benefit from them! Amen!).</p>

<p>The jurisconsult Abu-Abdullah-Anda-Ag-Mohammed<ref target="1"/>-ben-Mohammed-ben-'Otsmân-ben-Mohammed-ben-Nouh, a treasure trove of science, merits and virtues. From him came many masters of science and holy people: some from his father's side, others from his mother's side and others from both sides at the same time. This illustrious scholar was a cadi of the Muslims.</p>.

<p>The most learned jurisconsult Ahmed-Baba (God have mercy on him!) said, "This was the first of my ancestors</p>

<note n="1">It would be more in keeping with the literal transcription of the word to say "Ghamohammed"; but, here again, the initial vowel of the word has disappeared and Gha is put for Ag which means: "son".</p>

<pb n="76"/>

<p>48 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>who devoted himself to science, as far as I can tell; he was my paternal great-great-grandfather, the father of my grandfather's mother. He was appointed to the office of cadi of Timbuktu in the middle of the ninth century. - I add that at that time the Tuareg reigned in this city. - After him, Ahmed-Baba continues, it was 'Omar, the father of my grandfather; he was also a jurisconsult, a theologian, a pious character; he had followed the courses of the jurisconsult, the virtuous cadi Mouaddib-Mohammed-El-Kabari. Here ends the quote in summary of the words of the jurisconsult Ahmed-Baba.</p>

<p>The son of the previous one, the jurisconsult El-Mokhtâr, grammarian and scholar in all branches of science (<foreign>ra</foreign>). He was, as well as his father, the contemporary of the jurisconsult of the scholar, the pole, the holy personage in God, Sidi Yahya-Et-Tâdelsi (God have mercy on all of them and show them his satisfaction!). He died towards the end of the year 922 (1516).</p>

<p>The brother of the previous one, the jurisconsult Abderrahman. - He thoroughly possessed the Tehdib<ref target="1"/> of El-Berâdi'i. A pious and gentle man, he died without leaving any posterity other than an only daughter.</p>

<p>The grandson of Abu-Abdullah, Abu-'1.'Abbâs-AhmedBoryo-ben-Ahmed-ben-Anda-Ag-Mohammed. This pious scholar detached himself from the goods of this world and lived in the greatest humility. He was the teacher of a great number of masters of science among the modern inhabitants of Sankore (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>Another grandson of Abu-Abdullah, named Abu-Abdullah-Anda-Ag-Mohammed, son of the jurisconsult El-</p>

<note n="1">The full title of this work of Malekite law is <foreign>digub colors wie abelistil</foreign> composed in 372 (982) by Abu-Sa'id-Khalaf-ben-Aboul-Qasim-ElBerâdi i.</note>

<pb n="77"/>

<p>CHAPTER NINE</p>

<p>Mokhtar, the grammarian, the son of Anda-Ag-Mohammed, was imam of the mosque of Sankore; he was appointed to this post by the Sheikh-el-Islam, the father of blessings, the jurisconsult and cadi Mahmud, when the latter, on account of his great age, resigned his office. He was a shy, modest, humble scholar, full of trust in God and known by his knowledge of the Arabic language: he celebrated the glory of the Prophet (may God shower his blessings on him and grant him salvation!) and during Ramadan, in the mosque of Sankore he used to give a complete reading of the book of Cadi 'Iyad, entitled: Ech-Chifa<ref target="1"/> (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>Abou-Abdallah-Mohammed, son of Imam AndaAg-Mohammed, the panegyrist of the Prophet and the reader of the book of Ech-Chifa of the caïd 'Tyâd in the mosque of Sankoré after the death of his father; he fulfilled this office there until his death (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>The jurisconsult El-Mokhtâr-ben-Mohammed, son of the jurisconsult, grammarian El-Mokhtar-ben-AndaAg-Mohammed, the panegyrist of the Prophet. He paid bards on the occasion of the Prophet's nativity feast and took the greatest pleasure in hearing them; he occupied himself with this with the greatest activity until his death (God have mercy on him!).</p>.

<p>The son of the previous one, the jurisconsult, MuhammadSan, son of the jurisconsult El-Mokhtàr, the chief of the panegyrists. He took care to continue his father's work until his death and always displayed great dignity in this office. He was a good man, prominent, pious, devout, modest, well-mannered and exact (<foreign>r.</foreign>) in fulfilling his promises and commitments. From the time of his early jubilee until the end</p>

<note n="1">The full title of this well-known work is.
<foreign>; الشفاء بتعريف حقوق المصطفی :

</foreign> it celebrates the merits of the Prophet and provides much information about his life (cf. Haddji-kballa, 1. JV, p. 56).</note>

<p>(flistory of the Sudan.)</p>

<pb n="78"/>

<p>50 HISTORY OF SUDAN</p>

<p>of his life, he practiced all these virtues. Praise be to God for this! He was descended from the jurisconsult Anda-AgMohammed the elder (or the great) on his father's and mother's sides. His mother was the daughter of the jurisconsult, the Imam, Anda-Ag-Mohammed. Likewise the jurisconsult, cadi Mohammed-Qarayenki and his brother, the jurisconsult, cadi Sidi Ahmed, both had the daughter of the jurisconsult, imam Anda-Ag-Mohammed as their mother, and their father was the jurisconsult Anda-Ag-Mohammed, the son of the jurisconsult Anda-Ag-Mohammed-ben-Ahmed-ben-Boryo-ben-Ahmed, the son of the jurisconsult Anda-Ag-Mohammed the great. This blessed imam had five blessed daughters who all gave birth to blessed men: first the two just named; the third was the mother of the master of masters, of the imam of the mosque of Sankore, the jurisconsult Mohammed-ben-Mohammed-Korai; the fourth gave birth to the bearer<ref target="1"/> of the holy book, Mohammed-benYomzoghorbir; finally the fifth was the mother of AhmedMâtina-ben-Asikala, brother of Atakorai<ref target="2"/>. </p>

<p>The jurisconsult Aboul-'Abbâs-Ahmed-ben-Anda. Ag-Mohammed-ben-Mohammed, son of the jurisconsult Anda-Ag-Mohammed the great. He was a pure and wise man, educated in various branches of science, law, grammar, poetry, etc. (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>Abou-Mohammed-Abdallah, son of the jurisconsult Ahmed-Boryo-ben-Ahmed, son of the jurisconsult Anda-AgMohammed the Great. - He was descended from this personage by the paternal and maternal sides; his mother was the sister of the jurisconsult Aboul-'Abbâs-Ahmed-ben-Anda-Ag-Mohammed. Mufti of his time, grammarian, lexicographer, modest man, he was famous in his time for his knowledge</p>.

<note n="1">Those who know the Qur'an by heart are so called.</p> <p>

<note n="2">Or "Mâtini," according to mss. A and B.</note>

<pb n="79"/>

<p>CHAPTER NINE</p>

<p>Significance of the Qur'an and the notary<ref target="1"/> (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>Three of the grandsons by their mothers of the previous one. These sheikh-al-islam, these learned imams were: the jurisconsult Abdullah; the jurisconsult El-Hâdj-Ahmed and the jurisconsult Mahmud, all three sons of the jurisconsult 'Omarben-Mohammed-Aqit. The scholar in God, the pole Sidi Mohammed-El-Bekri, said about these three characters: "Ahmed was a saint; Mohammed was a saint; Abdallah was a saint. The latter would be well known as a saint) if he had not lived in a village<ref target="2"/>; for he remained in Tâzekhta until his death. He had recommended that his body should not be washed by anyone except his disciple Ibrahim, grandfather of Habib-ben-Mohammed-Baba. When Ibrahim came to perform his funeral task, he found a lighted lamp next to the deceased. He then said to the family members, "Where done (<foreign>ro</foreign>) is the sheikh's rosary?" It was brought to him. Then he had the lamp extinguished and put the rosary in its place. A bright light came out of this rosary and illuminated the room until the end of the washing of the body. El-HâdjAhmed was one of the pious servants of God and a practicing doctor.</p>

<p>As for Mahmud, he is the author of many prodigies and blessings. How often, invoked in deserted places to ward off danger or accident, he appeared and cleared the one who called him. When his elder brother El-Hâdj-Ahmed (God have mercy on him and help us for his sake!) was buried, he returned home so saddened that he did not pay any attention to the people who came to offer him their condolences. When he arrived in front of the house of Otsmân-Thảleb, he sighed deeply and cried out:</p>

<note n="1">The art of drawing up deeds and contracts, which forms one of the branches of Muslim law.</note>

<note n="2">In place of this sentence the text simply says: "if it were not that he was in a village."</note>

<pb n="80"/>



<p>"Now my brother Ahmed has left me, he is with the angels." Everyone understood that he saw the angels and that is why he was saddened. This is a remarkable kind of prodigy and divination.</p>

<p>The main person who attended Mahmud's meetings was the jurisconsult El-Mosalli, whose real name was Anda-Ag-Mohammed-ben-Mellouk-ben-Ahmedben-El-Hâdj-Ed-Doleïmi from the family of the Zawiya in Morocco and who was called<ref target="1"/> also the maternal grandfather of the jurisconsult Mahmud. His nickname was El-Mosalli<ref target="2"/> because of the many prayers he made in the mosque. This El-Mosalli reported the following: I had formed the project of asking the sheikh for the hand of one of his daughters and I had written my request with the intention of giving it to him when all the ordinary audience had withdrawn and we were alone. No sooner were we alone than he spoke first and said, "Birds that are of the same species are the only ones that fly together." I understood then that he had guessed my project and I abandoned it. El-Mosalli (God have mercy on him!) died in the year 995 (1587); at that time the very learned, the jurisconsult, the cadi Abu Hafs-'Omar, had held the office of cadi for two years.</p>

<p>Abou - Hafs - 'Omar-ben - El - Hâdj-Ahmed-benOmar-ben-Mohammed-Aqît, the grammarian;he constantly praised the Prophet in the morning and evening and every day of Ramadan<ref target="3"/>, he read in full in the mosque of Sankore the book of Ech-Shifa. He was benevolent to his family and very attached to his relatives, inquiring about their health and visiting them</p>

<note n="1">That is, instead of calling him by his name, when speaking about him, they used to say: the grandfather of Mahmud.</p>

<note n="2">"Mosalli" means "one who prays."</note>

<note n="3">The usage has continued of these pious readings done in the mosque during Ramadan.

</note>

<pb n="81"/>

<p>CILAPTER NINE 53</p>

<p>during their illnesses. He welcomed with the same open face great and small. He perished a martyr<ref target="1"/> in the city of Merrakech (God have mercy on him, show him satisfaction, cool his grave<ref target="2"/> (<foreign>qq</foreign>) and make him dwell in a wide abode in the highest of paradise!)</p> <p>

<p>The father of the preceding, A bou-Bekr, known as Aboukar-Bir-ben-El-Hâdj-Ahmed-ben-Omarben-Mohammed-Aqît. - He was a scholar, ascetic and charitable, and provided for orphans and students. During his reign<ref target="2"/> he emigrated with all his wives and children to be closer to the Messenger of God (God shower his blessings on him and grant him salvation!). In his love for God and his Prophet, he settled in the noble city of Medina and remained there, with all his family, in the neighborhood of the Chosen One<ref target="3"/>, until his death.</p>.
<p>He had already conceived the design of taking his whole family with him on his first pilgrimage to Mecca; he had even taken them out of the city and led them some distance away, when the cadi, the righteous El-Aqib, knowing that Abonkar would not return and not wishing to part with them permanently, compelled the family to remain. But on his second pilgrimage, as El-'Aqib had died, Abubar left with all his people and went to settle in the vicinity of the noble city of Medina and all of them remained there until they died.</p>.
<p>Here is one of the prodigies that Aboukar performed: His brother, the very learned jurisconsult Ahmed-ben-El-Hàdj-Akmed had</p>

<note n="1">The word <foreign>dogi</foreign> is usually applied to one who dies in a battle against the enemies of the faith; but it can also be understood as one who perishes as a victim of an accident.</p> <p>

<note n="2">Molà word: "in the days of his dynasty". Are we to assume that these words apply to a prince whom the author does not name, or is he referring to the series of characters of the Aqit family who formed a kind of dynasty? It is impossible to specify anything in this regard, given the lexicon.</note>

<note n="3">That is, in the vicinity of Muhammad's tomb.</note>

<pb n="82"/>



<p>asked the father of blessings, the saint in God, the pole, Sidi Mohammed El-Bekri (God have mercy on them all and show them his satisfaction!) to show him one of the saints of God whose support he could obtain from the Lord. El-Bekri granted him this favor. One night, after performing, in the mosque of El-Azhar<ref target="1"/>, the second evening prayer, as he was about to leave the mosque, El-Bekri who was holding the jurisconsult Ahmed by one hand, put that hand on the head of a man sitting there in the darkness saying, "This is what you asked me!" Ahmed sat down before this man, greeted him and recognized his brother Aboukar-Bir. He talked with him for a moment; then he went out and found El-Bekri waiting for him at the door of the mosque. This is the one you wanted to show me," he said. - Yes," he replied, "every night he performs the second evening prayer here."</p>

<p>The brother of the previous one, the very learned, the traditionist, the jurisconsult, Ahmed-ben - El - Hâdj - Ahmed - benOmar-ben-Mohammed-A qît. - This eloquent scholar was a beautiful man. God had given him perfection in all kinds of beauty, poise, complexion and (<foreign>mv</foreign>) voice. He was a calligrapher and a wonderful discourse on literature, law and traditions. He celebrated the praises of the Prophet (God shower salvation and blessings upon him!). He used to read the two Sahih<ref target="2"/> in the mosque of Sankore. He was much loved by all and held in great esteem. It will suffice, as a testimony to this esteem and reputation, to quote what the saintly, virtuous Abu-Abdullah-Mohammed-El-Bekri said about him in a poem that he sent at the time of parting with him. Here are these verses:</p>

<note n="1">The El-Azhar Mosque in Cairo is at the same time the seat of one of the most famous Muslim universities.</p> <p>

<note n="2">The two collections of traditions of El-Bokbûri and Moslem.</note>

<pb n="83"/>

<p>CHAPTER NINE 55</p>

<p>( our dear friends, by God! I am true to my promise; my friendship for you is all my friendship, and my affection for you, all my affection.</p>

<p>I have not forgotten the sweetness of the days when we were near each other, nor the moments we spent in gay or serious talk.</p>

<p>Certainly, I speak of you and I address God to grant you all that you desire.</p>

<p>At all blessed times, I ask him to fulfill all that you desire of his broad favors.</p>

<p>May he give you life, faith and your children; and, whatever you desire from his munificence, may he grant it to you without limit.</p>

<p>The children of Sheikh-el-Islam, the source of blessings the saint of God, the jurisconsult, the cadi, Mahmud-benOmar-ben-Mohammed-Aqit were: the cadi Muhammad, the cadi El-`Aqib, the cadi 'Omar, the jurisconsult Abdullah, the holy ascetic, the jurisconsult Abderrahman. The blessing of Islam, the jurisconsult 'Omar-Anda-Ag-Mohammed and the eminent sheikh, the jurisconsult Baba-Masira-Bir said, "Mahmud-ben-'Omar has graced us with nothing but virtuous children."</p>

<p>The Cadi Muhammad. - This illustrious scholar was of remarkable intelligence and sagacity. During his lifetime no one was found who could equal him in intelligence, shrewdness and good sense. He was favored by fortune (<foreign>re</foreign>). From the day after the day of his birth he had in his possession 1000 mitsqâls of gold from the gifts offered by those who rejoiced at his coming into the world, for he was the first male child of the source of blessings, the jurisconsult Mahmud.</p>

<p>The cadi El-Aqib. - An illustrious scholar, a penetrating mind, an energetic and firm man in matters of equity, he feared no criticism when it came to his duties to Dien. He was of remarkable insight and seemed to read the future, for whenever he announced any thing it did not fail to happen. He reigned</p>

<pb n="84"/>



<p>justice throughout his country, and in no place in the world was he equaled in this respect.</p>

<p>The cadi Abu-Hafs-'Omar. - He distinguished himself in the science of traditions, biographies, annals and history. In law he attained the highest degree of knowledge, so much so that a sheikh of his contemporaries said of him, "If he had lived at the time of Ibn Abd-es-Selâm in Tunis he would have deserved to occupy in that city the office of mufti."</p> <p>

<p>Abdullah was a learned jurisconsult and teacher. - Despite the great wealth with which God had graced him, so much so that he did not know the amount of his fortune, he was very sober from the pleasures of this world.</p> <p>

<p>The virtuous sheikh, the saint, the good counselor, the learned in God, the son of the previous one, the devout, the pious, the ascetic, the modest, the preacher Abu Zeid-Abderrahman, was a learned jurisconsult who disdained in such an absolute way the goods of this world, that he did not want to hold them even for a moment. He was gifted with second sight and the students of his medrasa tell, in this regard, many anecdotes, among them the following one which has been quoted many times:</p>.

<p>When the army of pasha Juder left the city of Merrakech, Abu Zeid announced this event on the very day it occurred, Wednesday, the 2nd of the month of Moharrem, the first month of the year 999 (October 31, 1590). He did so in the following way: When he had finished the dohor prayer with everyone, he sat down in his medrasa and said, "By God! By God! By God! you will hear something this year that you have never heard, and see what you have never seen." In the month of Jomada Jer of that same year (February 25-March 27, 1591), Moroccan troops arrived in Sudan and did what is known</p>

<pb n="85"/>

<p>CHAPTER NINE 57</p>

<p>(God preserve us from a new trial of this kind!). Abu-Zeed has to his credit many similar predictions.</p> <p>

<p>The jurisconsult, the learned, the divine, the holy virtuous Abu-'l-'Abbâs-Ahmed, son of the jurisconsult MuhammadEs-Sa'id, grandson, born of the daughter, of the jurisconsult Mahmud; he was famous (<foreign>wo</foreign>) in his time by his erudition, and a host of learned masters of science came to attend his talks to learn from his lessons. Among them were: the cadi 'Omar, son of the jurisconsult Mahmond, the jurisconsult Mohammed-Bagh yo'o-El-Ouankori, his brother the jurisconsult Ahmed-Baghyo'o, the jurisconsult Ko'ti, the jurisconsult Mohammed-Kibba, son of Djâ ber-Kibba, etc. All of them are unanimous in testifying to the knowledge, mastery, reserve and virtue of Abu 'l-'Abbâs (God have mercy on him and perpetuate his blessings on us and on Muslims!)</p>.

<p>The grandson of the previous one, the learned juriscusult Abu-Bekr-ben-Ahmed-ben-Bir, son of the juriscusult Mahmud, was an eminent, good, pious and virtuous man, and that from a young age, as his virtuous paternal uncles declared. Everyone agreed to make him preside over the public prayer during the illness of the Imam, dn cadi El-'Aqib. God have mercy on him!</p>

<p>The jurisconsult, the scholar, the very learned, the jewel of his time and the only one of his time, the outstanding man in all branches of science, Abu-'l-'AbbasAhmed-Baba, son of the jurisconsult Ahmed-ben-El-HâdjAhmed-ben-'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqit. He displayed the greatest zeal and intelligence from the beginning of his studies, so that he rose above his contemporaries and surpassed them all by far. He had controversies about science only with his teachers and they testified to his knowledge. His worth was famous in MaCOI</p>

<pb n="86"/>



<p>ghreb and his fame spread far and wide. All the doctors of the great cities recognized his superiority in fetuah. He was rigorously just even to the humblest of men; he never concealed what was right, even from the emirs or the sultans. The name of Mohammed was written on his right forearm in white lines naturally formed on the skin. All those we have mentioned from the biography of the blessed sheikh, the jurisconsult Anda-Ag-Mohammed the great, until this moment, were from his blessed race and virtuous family God have mercy on them all, show them his satisfaction and make us enjoy their blessings in this world and the next!)</p>).

<p>As for the grandfather of the jurisconsult Mahmud, Mohammed-Aqît, he was a native of Mâsina. I heard the jurisconsult Ahmed-Baba (God have mercy on him! ) that "Mohammed-Aqit left the Masina to go to Biro only because of the hatred of the Fulani<ref target="1"/>, who lived in the vicinity of his dwelling, that he was certain that there had never been a marriage between his family and the Fulani (<foreign>7</foreign>), but that he feared that his children would not do the same, and that thus their lineage would be mixed with Fulani blood. )</p>

<p>Later, he felt the desire to live in Timbuktu. This was at the time when Sultan Akil ruled. He left Biro, came to set up his tent between Biro and Ras-el-ma, and as he was talking with Masira-Anda-'Omar's grandfather, the latter said to him, "Who is preventing you from going to this city? - He replied, "Because there is a strong enmity between Akil and me. - Well, God willing," said his interlocutor, "I will be the cause that will put an end to this enmity and you will live in Tom-</p>

<note n="1">Or: Peuls, Foulbés, which are only different spellings of the same word.</p> <pb

<pb n="87"/>

<p>CHAPTER NINE 59</p>

<p>Buckwheat as it is your desire," Thereupon he went to find Akil at his camp, introduced himself to him, and began to talk about various things; then announced to him that Mohammed-Agit had no greater desire at this moment than to live in Timbuktu. - That's not possible," cried Akil. - And why is that?" replied Masira's grandfather. Then, entering his tent, Akil soon came out with a shield all lacerated with spear and saber blows. "See," he added, "what Mohammed-Aqit has done to me. How can a man live in the same city as an enemy who has treated him like this? -- Let it go, then; all that you say there is past. Today this man is poor; he has a large family and he only wants to live in peace." Then he added so many gentle and persuasive words that Akil's hatred subsided and he allowed MohammedAqît to come to Timbuktu. Masira's grandfather went to find his friend, told him what had happened; Mohammed and his family set out and came to stay in Timbuktu.</p> <p>Among the shepherds of the region, there was a great deal of interest in the history of the region.

<p>Among the blessed sheikhs of Sankore was the jurisconsult, Ahmed, son of the jurisconsult Ibrahim-benAbou-Bekr, son of the cadi El-Hâdj, father of Mama-Siri. It is reported that our sheikh, the ascetic, the jurisconsult El-Amînben-Ahmed, brother of the jurisconsult Abderrahman, would have said: "The sheikh Ahmed would only suspend his lessons on the Koran to teach theology. He used all his moments for this holy occupation" (God have mercy on him, show him his satisfaction, and shower some of his blessings on us!)</p>.

<p>The jurisconsult, the virtuous, the son of Muhammad-Anda-'Omar known as Sâlih-Takounni. - This sheikh visited and honored by the sultans interceded with them in favor of the unfortunate and in no circumstances</p>

<pb n="88"/>

<p>60 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>his intercession was not repelled. He composed a commentary on Sheikh Khelil's Mokhtasar<ref target="1"/> (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>The seyyid Abu 'l-'Abbâs-Ahmed-ben-Mohammed (<foreign>v</foreign>) ben-'Otsmân-ben-Abdallah-ben-AbouY'aqoub, - He was a learned jurisconsult, lexicographer, grammarian, scholar in literature, exe. gesis and poetry. Many sheikhs have testified to his science (God have mercy on him! Amen!).</p> <p>

</div> <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10"> <head>CHAPTER X BIOGRAPHIES OF THE SAVANTS OF TOMBOUCTOU</head>

<p>In his work entitled Edz-Dzil<ref target="2"/>, the very learned, jurisconsult Ahmed-Baba (God have mercy on him!) expresses himself thus: Ahmed-ben-Omar-ben-MohammedAqît-ben-'Omar-ben-'Ali-ben-Yahya-ben-Godâla<ref target="3"/>, the Senhadjian, the Timbuktuist, was my grandfather, the father of my father; he was referred to as El-Hàdj-Ahmed. He was the eldest of three brothers who distinguished themselves by their science and piety in their country. He was a good man, virtuous and pious, possessing in his memory the Sonna;</p>

<note n="1">This précis of Muslim law is in a way the code of the Malekites.</p> <p>

<note n="2">According to a passage in the <foreign>zalj Judd iso agged to list as Lås</foreign> (ms. Arabic no. 4628 of the National Library, 1° 283 10), Ahmed Baba says indeed that he composed a supplement
<foreign> (ذل) </foreign> it and the title he gives to it is as follows:

<foreign> .نيل الابتهاج تطريز :
</foreign> l. It is quite possible that the abbreviated name of this work <foreign>Jaill</foreign> was confused with <foreign>Jil</foreign>, a very easy confusion in Arabic script. A. Cherbonneau has published an Essay on Arabic literature in the Sudan, based on the Tekmil.t-ed- (liba'lj of Ahmed-Baba, the Tombouclian. Constantine et Paris, MDCCCLVI; one will find in this plate some of the biographies which will follow.</note>

<note n="3">We write lanlat
<foreign> ,حدالة
</foreign> tantot
<foreign> .كدالة
</foreign></note>

<pb n="89"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN</p>

<p>He was well brought up, chaste, distinguished, full of love for the Prophet and constantly compelled to read the poems in honor of Muhammad and the Shifa of "Iyàd. Jurisconsult, lexicographer, grammarian, prosodist and scholar, he occupied himself with science all his life. His books were numerous, written in his own hand with copious annotations. At his death he left about 700 volumes. He had studied under his maternal grandfather, the jurisconsult Anda-Ag-Mohammed and under his maternal uncle, the jurisconsult El-Mokhtàr, the grammarian, and under still other masters.</p>.

<p>He traveled to the East in the year 890 (1485) and made the pilgrimage to Mecca. There he met El-Djelâl-Es-Soyouti and Sheikh Khàled-El-Ouaqqâd-El-Azhari, the prince of grammarians, and other characters. He returned at the time of the revolt of the Karedjite Sovni-'Ali, visited Kano and other cities of Sudan. He taught theology and was successful in his teaching, from which many people benefited, among whom the most illustrious was the jurisconsult Mahmoud to whom he taught among other things the Modaouana<ref target="1"/>. He was a scholar of the first order as a teacher and scholar. He worked until his death which took place on a Thursday evening in the month of rebi' II of the year 943 September-October 1536); he was then about 80 years old. He was offered the office of imam, but he refused it, as well as other lesser jobs.</p>

<p>One of his most famous miracles is the following: When he visited the noble tomb (of the Prophet), he asked (<foreign>vw</foreign>) to go inside the monument. The guard prevented him from doing so. He then sat outside and began to praise the Prophet. Immediately the door opened by itself without any apparent cause. Instantly there was a rush around him</p>.

<note n="1">Malekite law treatise by Sahnoun, cadi of Qairun.</p> <pb

<pb n="90"/>

<p>62 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>to kiss his hand. This is how I heard this story told by several people<ref target="1"/>.</p>

<p>Abdallah-ben-'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqît ben-'Omar-ben-'Ali-ben-Yahya, the Senhadjian, the Messufite. - He was the first brother of my grandfather, Jurisconsilte, scholar, ascetic, modest man, virtuous, holy, of the greatest reserve, of the greatest piety and gifted with an excellent memory, he taught in Oualåten. He died in this city in the year 929 (1522- 1523); he was born in 866 (1461-1462). He performed some miracles<ref target="2"/>.</p>

<p>Mahmoud-ben - 'Omar-ben - Mohammed - Aqîtben-'Omar-ben-'Ali-ben - Yahya-ben - Godâla, the Senhadjian, the Timbuktu; cadi of Timbuktu, this father of praise and beautiful deeds was par excellence and without question the scholar, saint, teacher, jurisconsult and imam of the land of Tekrour<ref target="3"/> He was one of the best creatures of God among the saints and scholars in God. He had energetic firmness in all things, perfect orthodoxy, calmness, dignity and majesty.</p>

<p>His learning and virtues were famous in the land and his fame had spread to all lands, east, west, south and north. The gifts of heaven were manifested in his piety, his virtues, his asceticism and his cheerfulness. He did not fear criticism from any quarter when it came to God's commandments. Everyone respected him; the sultan as well as lesser personages were at his command; they visited him in his house, asked for his blessing without him</p>


<note n="1">This biography can be found on page 8 of the Essay on Arabic Literature ciu Soudun.</p> <p>

<note n="2">See the Essay, p. 9.</p> <p>

<note n="3">The name Tekrour is that of a province of the Sudan; but it is often used to designate the whole Sudan.</note>

<pb n="91"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN 63</p>

<p>went out of his way for them. They 'brought him money and gifts flocked to his house. He was liberal and generous,</p>

<p>He was appointed cadi in the year 904 (1498-1499). He dispensed good justice in all things, being energetic in favor of the right and threatening to those who were wrong. His justice was so famous that no one knew of his rival in this respect at that time. He was also a teacher. The law in his mouth was a gentle and easy thing, easy to understand, quick to assimilate, and imposing no fatigue<ref target="1"/>. Many people benefited from his lessons. Science, thanks to him, lived in his country; students of law became more numerous; many of them distinguished themselves in this study and became true scholars. The works that he especially made people study were: the Modaououana , the Risvila<ref target="2"/>, the Mokhtasar of Khelil, the Alfiya<ref target="3"/>, the Seláldjiya. He was the propagator of Khelil's work in the Sudan and covered his copy with annotations which one of his students published, in the form of a commentary, in two volumes.</p> <p>He was the author of the first volume of the book.

<p>He made the pilgrimage to Mecca in the year 915 (1510), and was in contact, during this journey, with masters, such as: Ibrahim-El-Moqadessi, Sheikh Zakariya, ElQalqachandi (disciples of Ibn-Hadjar), the two El-Laqqàni and others. There he made his merits appreciated, then he returned to his country where he applied himself to be useful (<foreign>ra</foreign>) and to make the right triumph. His life was long and he knew both fathers and sons.</p>

<p>He taught for about fifty years and did not stop until his death which occurred in 955 on Thursday evening, 16 of the month of Ramadan (October 19, 1548). He attained a high degree of fame and enjoyed a very high reputation. Fame</p>

<note n="1">The language of Muslim law is often obscure to the layman.</p> <p>

<note n="2">The Risala of Abu-Zeid-El-Qa'uraïni is a widely used work of Malekite law,</p> <note>

<note n="3">Arabic grammar in verse by Ibn-Malek.</note>

<pb n="92"/>



<p>of his virtues reached a point that none other than him reached. He was born in the year 868 (1463-1464). He was the teacher of my father (God have mercy on him!), of three of his children, the cadis Muhammad, El-`Aqib and Omar and many others.</p>

<p>Makhlouf-ben-'Ali-ben-Sâlih-El-Belbâli. - Jurisconsult, geographer<ref target="1"/>, he did not take up the study until an advanced age, so it is assured. The first of his teachers was the virtuous Sidi Abdallah-ben-'Omar-ben Mohammed-Aqit, the first brother of my grandfather who was then in Oualåten. He first studied Risala, then his master saw that he had great dispositions and encouraged him to continue his studies. Full of enthusiasm, he left for Morocco where he studied under Ibn-Ghazi and others. He was famous for the power of his memory, and about this there are astonishing stories.</p>.

<p>He traveled through the country of the Sudan, went among other places to Kano, Kachena, etc. He taught in these various localities and had discussions about known trials with the jurisconsult El-Aqib-El-Ansamanni. Then he went to Timbuktu where he also taught, then he returned to Morocco and taught a course in the city of Merrakech. Poisoned in that city, he fell ill and returned to his homeland where he died after the year 910 (1533-1534)<ref target="2"/>.</p>

<p>Mohammed-ben-Ahmed-ben-Abou-MohammedEt-Tazakhti, known as Aida-Ahmed. - Aïda, which is written with a hamza accompanied by an a, a ya without vowels, a dal with vowel a, is in annexation relationship with the name Ahmed and means son. Jurisconsult, theologian, traditionist, very sagacious and erudite man, excellent calligrapher, very much inclined to discussion with his keen intelli-</p>

<note n="1">Word for word: "knowing by heart of travel relations."</p> <p>

<note n="2">Cr. the Essay, p. i.</p>

<pb n="93"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN</p>

<p>Emergency, he studied in his country under my grandfather, the jurisconsult El-Hâdj-Ahmed-ben-'Omar and under his maternal uncle, the jurisconsult 'Ali and became a scholar.</p>

<p>At Takeda, he met Imam El-Moghili' and attended his classes, then he left for the East in the company of the jurisconsult Sidi Mahmoud and had the opportunity to enter into relations with illustrious scholars, such as: the sheikh-el-islam Zakariya, the dialectician El-Qalqachandi, Ibn-Abou-Sherif, Abdelhaqq-Es-Soubâți, and a quantity of others. He took from them lessons in hadith, listened to their oral teaching (<foreign>8 - </foreign>) and their discussions; he benefited so much from them that he was a distinguished teacher in all matters and deserved the title of traditionist.</p>

<p>He attended the course of the two brothers El-Laqqâni and became friends with Ahmed-ben-Mohammed and Abdelhaqq-Es-Soubâți. In Mecca he received degrees from the father of the blessings En-Nuairi, the latter's paternal cousin Abdelqader, Ali-ben-Naser-El-Hidjâzi, Abu-'t-Tayyeb-El-Bosţi and others. He then returned to the Sudan and settled in Kachena, whose sultan treated him with respect and entrusted him with the duties of cadi. He died around the year 936 (1529-1530), aged sixty or so. He is the author of annotations and marginal notes on the text of the Mokhtasar of Sheikh Khelil<ref target="2"/>.</p>

<p>Mohammed-ben-Mahmoud-ben-'Omar-ben-Mohammed- A qît-ben-'Omar-ben-'Ali-ben-Yahya, the Senhadjian, cadi of Timbuktu. - This jurisconsult was very intelligent, very sagacious; his piercing mind made him one of the most sensible and wise men. He succeeded</p>

<note n="1">Famous scholar from Tlemcen. His biography is given in the Essay, p. 10.
</note>

<note n="2">Cf. the Essay, p. 18.</note>



<pb n="94"/>



<p>to his father in the office of cadi. Fortune was favorable to him; he obtained all the honors he desired and amassed considerable property. He made a commentary on El-Moghili's poem in redjez on logic. My father had studied rhetoric and logic under him. He died in the month of safar of the year 973 (September 1565); he was born in 909 (1503- 1504).</p>

<p>El-Agîb-ben-Mahmoud-ben-'Omar-ben-Moham med-Aqît-ben- Omar-ben-'Ali-ben-Yahya, the Senhadjian, cadi of Timbuktu. - From a family of scholars and clergymen, he rendered justly reasoned judgments. Firm in the path of law, he did not fear any criticism when it came to the prescriptions of God. Very energetic and enterprising in the matters he dealt with, he resisted the Sultan as well as the others and did not take their observations into account. He had, in this respect, a number of adventures. Everyone was humble before him, feared him and obeyed everything he wanted. When he saw something that displeased him, he would withdraw to the side, close his door, and it was necessary to use great care for him to return. This happened to him frequently.</p>

<p>Gifted with great foresight in business, his perspicacity was never in default; it seemed as if he could see into the future. Very comfortable as a fortune, happy in all his undertakings, he was regarded, feared and highly respected. He took lessons from (<foreign>21</foreign>) his father and his paternal uncle. He made the pilgrimage to Mecca and then saw EnNâsir-El-Laqqâni, Abu'-l-Hasen-El-Bekri, Sheikh El-Baikouri' and their colleagues. El-Laqqâni issued him diplomas on all the subjects he taught either according to his .</p>

<note n="1">Or Bechkouri.</note>

<pb n="95"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN</p>

<p>His own sources, or from those of his teachers. He<ref target="1"/> issued me the same diplomas written in his hand. Muhammad was born in 913 (1507); he died in the month of redjeb in the year 991 (August 1583)<ref target="2"/>.</p> <p>

<p>El-'A qît-ben-Abdallah-El-Ansammani, the Messufite, a native of Takeda, a village populated by Senhadjians near the Sudan. He was a wise jurisconsult, with a fine intelligence and a sharp mind, and he devoted himself to science. He had a sharp tongue. He is the author of annotations of which the most remarkable is the one he made on these words of Khelil: "The intention of the one who swears must be specified. I have abridged this work by adding quotations taken from other authors and have made it into a volume to which I have given the title of : Tenbih el-oudgif'ala tahrir khossiset niyatou 'l-halif. He also published a treatise on the obligation of the Friday prayer in common in the village of Ansammani, contrary to the opinion of other authors: he was right. He is also the author of the books: El-djaouab el-medjdoud 'an as'ilat elqadi Mohammed-ben-Mahmoud and Adjouibat el-faqir 'an as'ilat el-émir, the latter in response to the Emir Askia-El-Hâdj-Mohammed, and other works. He had a discussion with the hafid El-Belbâli on certain questions. He was still living around the year 950 (1543).</p>

<p>Abou-Bekr-ben-Ahmed-Bir-ben-'Omar.ben-Mohammed-Aqît, a Timbuktuite by birth, he fixed his residence in the noble city of Medina. He was my paternal uncle. He was a good man, with a beautiful voice, reserved, ascetic, pious and God-fearing. He was a blessed saint known for his virtues, and of obvious piety, reserve, and kindness. Of strong faith, he practiced almsgiving and goodness a lot</p>.

<note n="1">This is Ahmed-Baba, whose text is reproduced, speaking.</p> <p>

<note n="2">Cf. the Essay, p. 20.</note>

<pb n="96"/>

<p>68 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>facility, rarely keeping anything back from himself despite his meager resources. He was of incomparable ardor for good and was so from his youth. He made the pilgrimage to Mecca and frequented the holy places, then returned to his country because of his children whom he brought back with him. After making the pilgrimage again, he settled in Medina where he remained until his death in early 991 (late January or February 1583); he was born in 932 (1526-1527). He was my first teacher of syntax; thanks to the divine protection which he enjoyed I made great progress and, in a short time, without effort, I became a master of this branch of science. He had glorious moments. Always fearful of God and careful to please him, he gave wise counsel to men. He was always sobbing (<foreign>Ev</foreign>) and his tongue moistened to praise God and often mentioned his name. Very open with everyone, he was one of the best saints on earth. He spurned fortune and deprived himself of its glitter, although he belonged to a family enjoying high regard. I have never seen his equal, nor even anyone who approaches him in merit. He left some small treatises on Sufism and other subjects<ref target="1"/>.</p>

<p>Ahmed-ben-Ahmed-ben-'Omar-ben-MohammedAqît-ben-'Omar-ben-Ali-ben-Yahya, my father. - He was a jurisconsult, a theologian, the son of a jurisconsult and a theologian, a fine and sagacious mind. He was a scholar, a traditionalist, he had studied everything, the theory of law, rhetoric, logic. He had a sensitive heart and was highly esteemed by the princes and the whole world. He was pleased to use his influence and never his intervention was rejected, He was firm towards kings as</p>

<note n="1">Cf. the Essay, p. 24.</p> <pb

<pb n="97"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN 69</p>

<p>in regard to others, so all had the deepest respect for him. They went to visit him at his home, and when, in one of his journeys, he fell ill at Kâgho, the great Sultan Askia-Daoud, in order to do him honor, came to see him every night to watch and talk with him until he was cured. His power and glory were famous; no one dared to resist him, so great was his authority. He loved good people and was humble with them, never hating anyone and doing justice to all. He was a lover of books; his well-stocked library contained all the rare and precious works; he willingly lent them.</p>

<p>He had taken lessons from his paternal uncle, the blessing of that time, Mahmoud-ben-'Omaret of other masters. He traveled to the East in the year 956 (1549); he made the pilgrimage to Mecca and visited the tomb of the Prophet. On this journey he came into contact with many scholars such as En-Nasir-El-Laqqâni, Sherif Youcef, disciple of Es-Soyouti, El-Djemal, son of Sheikh Zakariya, El-Adjhouri, Et-Tadjouri. In Mecca and Medina he met Amîn-eddîn-El-Meïmouni, El-Mellaï, Ibn-Hadjar, Abdelaziz-El-Lamti, Abdelmoʻti-Es-Sekhaouï, Abdelqader-El-Fakihi, etc. He benefited from the conversation of these scholars, but he especially frequented Aboul-Makârim-Mohammed-El-Bekri and enjoyed his divine protection. He noted a number of proposals of this master and then returned to his country, where he did some courses.</p>.

<p>He commented on the tekhmis<ref target="1"/> of the 'Achriniyrit el-fazaziya, a poem (er) in honor of the Prophet; he also made an excellent commentary on El-Moghili's poem on the lo-</p>

<note n="1">This kind of development of a piece of poetry consists of adding four lines to each of the lines of a poem so as to form stanzas of five lines.</note>

<pb n="98"/>

<p>70 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>graphics and glosses on a passage of Khelil; then he composed on the commentary of Et-Tataï, marginal glosses to show the inaccurate passages of that work; he commented again on the Soghra<ref target="1"/> of Es-Senousi, the Qortobiya<ref target="2"/>, the Djomel<ref target="3"/> of El-Khoundji on the osoul<ref target="4"/>, but he did not complete most of these works. For twenty and some years, during the month of redjeb and the following two months he explained the two Saħiħ. He died on Sunday evening, 17 of the month of Sha'ban in the year 991 (September 6, 1583).</p>

<p>As his speech had become embarrassed, one day when in the mosque he was reading the Sahiḥ of Moslem, our master the most learned Mohammed-Bagh yo'o, who was sitting opposite him, beckoned him to stop his reading. The following Monday he died. Among his many disciples are: the two virtuous jurisconsults, our master Mohammed and his brother Ahmed, both sons of the jurisconsult Mahmud-Baghyo'o; they studied under him osul, rhetoric and logic; the two jurisconsults and brothers Abdallah and Abderrahman, both sons of the jurisconsult Mahmud, and others. I myself attended his classes on many subjects and he gave me degrees on everything he taught according to his system or a borrowed system. I studied with him the two Sahih, the Muatļas<ref target="5"/> and the Shifa. He was born at the beginning of moharrem of the year 929 (November-December 1522). After his death (God have mercy on him!) I saw him in a beautiful dream<ref target="6"/>.</p>

<note n="1">Short title of a work on the dogmas of the faith composed by Mohammcd-ben-Youcef-Es-Senousi; the full title is:<foreign>siell ödeel.</foreign></note>

<note n="2">Poem that deals with the duties of the Muslim.</note>

<note n="3">Treaty on logic by Ibn-Nâmâwar-El-Khoundji.</note>

<note n="4">This is the name given to the science that deals with the theory of law or the principles from which it is derived.</note>

<note n="5">Title of a collection of traditions published after Malik-ben-Anas, the founder of the Malekite doctrine.</note>

<note n="6">Cf. the Essay, p. 21.</note>

<pb n="99"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN 71</p>

<p>Ahmed-ben-Mohammed-ben-Sa'id, son of the daughter of the jurisconsult Mahmud-ben-'Omar. - A jurisconsult, theologian, scholar and teacher, he once attended his grandfather's lessons on Risala and the Mokhtasar of Khelil. He studied under other masters the Mokhtasar and the Modaouquama. The people benefited from his talents from the year 960 (1553) until the time of his death, which occurred in moharrem, the first month of the year 976 (July 1568).</p>.

<p>The jurisconsult, our master Muhammad and his brother Ahmed also a jurisconsult. -- The latter studied under the previous<ref target="1"/> the Mouatta, the Modaououana, the Mokhtasar of Khelil and other works. He is the author of a marginal gloss on Khelil where he deals with both form and substance. He was born in 931 (1524-1525). I knew him as a young man and attended his class.</p>.

<p>Mohammed-ben-Mahmoud-ben-Abou-Bekr, the Quankori, the Timbuktu. - He is better known as Baghyo'o (ba with the vowel a, ghain with the djezm, ya with the vowel o and 'ain with the vowel o). He was our master and protector. A jurisconsult, theologian, scholar, virtuous, pious, devout (<foreign>2x</foreign>), he was one of God's best virtuous creatures, a practicing scholar, a man imbued with goodness; he was of perfect loyalty, of a pure nature. He was so inclined to goodness and to believe that everyone was like him that he had an excellent opinion of others and regarded them, so to speak, as his equals in good feeling and having no knowledge of evil.</p>.

<p>He cared for the affairs of others, harming himself when necessary to do them a favor. He was forgiving of their fai-</p>

<note n="1">This notice is very poorly written. After speaking of the two brothers at the beginning, only one is mentioned, and the name of the character under whom the author studied is indicated only by a pronoun that seems to refer to the scholar Ahmed, whose biography alone is given.</p> <pb>

<pb n="100"/>



<p>blessings, sought to bring them into agreement, and urged them to love science, to follow its teachings, to employ all their moments in it, to frequent the scholars, and to be of perfect docility. He lavished on all his books the most precious, the rarest and the most precious to him; he never asked for them afterwards, no matter what science they dealt with. In this way, he lost a great number of his books (God be thankful to him!). Sometimes a student would come to his door and ask for a book, and he would give it away without even knowing who he was dealing with. It was truly amazing that he did this; he did it to be pleasing to God, despite the passion he had for books, which he collected ardently either by buying them or by having them copied.</p>.

<p>One day I went to him to ask him for some grammar books. He searched his library and gave me all those he could find. He had great patience for teaching; he devoted every moment of the day to it and and when it came to getting a bachelor to learn something useful, he was never discouraged or put off. Those present were obsessed with it, but he did not care. It was so much so that one day I heard one of our fellow students, astonished at his patience, say: "I believe that this jurisconsult drank the water of Zemzem<ref target="1"/> so as not to be put off by the teaching." This did not prevent him from devoting himself to acts of piety.</p>

<p>He did not believe in the bad faith of people and always thought well of others as long as they had not committed any fault and even if they had committed some fault. He was concerned only with what was his business and refrained from taking part in gossip; he draped himself in the most</p>

<note n="1">The waters of the well of Zemzem, a well located within the precincts of the temple of Mecca, are said to have the power to cure many ills and to give many virtues.</p> <pb

<pb n="101"/>

<p>CHAPTER TENTH 73</p>

<p>magnificent mantle of discretion and reserve. He held firm in hiså hand the solid standard of continence. Calm and dignified, of an elite nature and a modesty that made it easy to deal with him, he had won over all hearts. Everyone was unanimous in making the most of him. One saw only people in love with him, glorifying him and sincerely praising him.</p> <p>His longanimity was a great help to the people.

<p>His longanimity was such that he would never refuse to teach a beginner or a narrow-minded person. He spent his whole life teaching while actively engaged in the affairs of the people and the affairs of the cadis. One could not have found a replacement for him or met his equal.</p>.

<p>- The sultan offered him the government of his palace<ref target="1"/>; he refused to accept the offer made to him and rejected it after insisting to the prince (<foreign>20</foreign>); he was thus delivered by God from this concern.</p>

<p>He devoted himself to teaching especially after the death of Sidi Ahmed-ben-Mohammed-ben-Said. When I knew him, he would start his classes immediately after the morning prayer and continue them until the great doha<ref target="2"/> varying the subjects he treated. Then he would return home and perform the doha prayer; then, sometimes, he would then go to the cadi to attend to people's affairs or reconcile them among themselves. After that he would continue to teach at his house until noon; he would say the dohor prayer with all the faithful and would resume his lessons until the asr. After this last prayer, he would go to another place to teach again until dusk or close to it. After the maghreb<ref target="3"/> he would teach</p>

<note n="1">Mss. A and B give also which means "army". It would not be impossible, moreover, for the prince to have thought of entrusting him with the command of his troops; it is known that the cadi Asad led an expedition to Sicily. The ms. C writes Jso and the meaning would then be "palace"; this latter reading is more likely than the former.</note>

<note n="2">The doha takes place at about half past nine of the evil,</note>

<note n="3">The sunset prayer.</note>

<pb n="102"/>



<p>would stay in the mosque until acha<ref target="1"/> and then he would go home. I even heard that he always came to the mosque at the end of the night.</p>

<p>Subtle mind, sagacious, fine, alert, meticulous, quick to reply, quick to understand, of a luminous intelligence, he was taciturn, silent, serious. Sometimes, however, he would lighten up, or he would throw at his listeners some line that testified to his well-known intellectual superiority and the promptness of his understanding. He had learned Arabic, and law from two virtuous jurisconsults, his father and his maternal uncle.</p>

<p>At the same time as his brother, the virtuous jurisconsult Ahmed, he settled in Timbuktu. Both assiduously followed the lessons of the jurisconsults Ahmed-ben-Mohammedben-Sa'id on the Mokhtasar of Khelil; then they went on a pilgrimage to Mecca with their maternal uncle. In this journey they met En-Nâsir-El-Laqqâni, Et-Tadjouri, Sherif Yuf-El-Aumayouni, El-Barahamouchi<ref target="2"/> the hana fite, Imam Mohammed-El-Bekri and other scholars and enjoyed their talks. They returned to their country on the death of their maternal uncle and, after performing the pilgrimage, they settled in Timbuktu, where they studied, under the guidance of Ibn-Sa'ïd, law and tradition. With him they explained the Mouatta, the Modaououana, the Mokhtasar, etc. With my father, they studied the Osul, rhetoric and logic explaining the Osul of Es-Sebki and the Telkhis el-miftah<ref target="3"/>. Then, after the death of his brother, Muhammad alone also studied with my father the Djomel of El-Khoundji. At the same time he indulged in teaching-</p>

<note n="1">The prayer that takes place at dusk.</p> <p>

<note n="2">Or: "El-Barahamnouch", according to the ms. C.</note>

<note n="3">The <foreign>chiell vent</foreign> is a rhetorical treatise by Djelål-ed-Dîn-Mohammed-EiQazouîni.</note>

<pb n="103"/>

<p>CHAPTER TENTH 75</p>

<p>really and later became the greatest master of his time without anyone being able to compare to him.</p>

<p>I assiduously attended his classes for more than ten years; I saw with him about eight times the whole of Khelil's Mokhtasar with the interpretations he gave of it (<foreign>in</foreign>) and those he held from others. I studied with him, so as to have a complete understanding of it, the Mouatta; the Teshil<ref target="1"/> of IbnMâlek, which I examined thoroughly and from all sides for three years; the Osul of Es-Sebki with the commentary of El-Mahalli, seen thoroughly three times; the Alfiya<ref target="2"/> of El-Iraqi with commentary by the author; the Telkhis el-miftah with the abridgement of Es-Saad, twice, at least; the Soghra of Es-Senousi; the commentary of El-Djezaïriya<ref target="3"/>; the Hikem<ref target="4"/> of Ibn-'AtaAllah, with commentary by Zerrouq; the Nadm<ref target="5"/> of Abu-Mogra'a and the Hashemiya on astrology with their commentaries; the Moqaddima<ref target="6"/> of Et-Tadjouri on this subject; the Redjez<ref target="7"/> of El-Moghili on logic; the Khazeredjia<ref target="8"/> on metrics, with the commentary of Es-Sibti sheriff; a large part of Ibn-'Acem's Tohfat el-hokkám<ref target="9"/> with the commentary of the author's son; all according to his interpretations. I</p>

<note n="1">The full title is:<foreign> dolell Jalig weill changes.</foreign> It is a prose grammar treatise composed by the author of the Alfiya, Djemâl-el-Din-Mohammedibn-Malek.</note>

<note n="2">Treaty in verse on traditions, by Abd-er-Rahim-ben-El-Hosaïn-El-Atsiri El-Iraqi.</note>

<note n="3">Poem on the unity of God by <foreign>s salti alii dus is dole</foreign></note>

<note n="4">Trail of morality and mysticism by 'Ata-Allah-Tâdj-ed-Din-Ahmed ElIskenderâni-Ech-Chadzili. The title is:<foreign> albell mbl.</foreign></note>

<note n="5">Probably the poem of <foreign>this gul</foreign> on the calculation of nativities.
</note>

<note n="6">Probably the work entitled: <foreign>cell als j dades</foreign> by Mohammed-ben-Idris. It is a treatise for determining the time of prayers.</note>

<note n="7">This is probably the poem given as number 11 in the list given by Cherbonneau (see Essay, p. 13).</note>

<note n="8">Didactic poem on prosody by Diya-ed-Dîn-Abdallah-ben-Mohammed-El-Khazradji.</note>

<note n="9">Malekite law treatise in verse (cf. 0. Houdas and F. Martel, La Tohfat d'Ebn-Acem, texte et traduction, Alger, 1882).</note>

<pb n="104"/>

<p>76 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>Also studied with him the Fera'ï<ref target="1"/> of Ibn Fl-Hâdjeb, a comprehensive and critical study. I attended his lectures on the Taudih<ref target="2"/>, but he explained only a part of it from the chapter of the deposit to the chapter of the judgments. I studied with him a large part of El-Bâdji's El-Montega; the Modaououana with commentary of Abu-'l-Hasen-Ez-Zerouaili, the Shifa of Iyâd ; half of the Sahih of El-Bokhari with his interpretation and the whole of the Sahih of Moslim on several occasions; the Modkhel of Ibn El-Hâdjeb<ref target="3"/>; finally I attended some of his lessons on the Risala, the Alfiya, etc. I commented with him on the sublime Qur'an up to the middle of the sura of A'raf<ref target="4"/>; I heard him read the entire Djam i el-mi'yárs<ref target="5"/> of El-Ouancherisi, a work which forms a large volume, and other matters. I often discussed with him on doubtful points and had recourse to his science on important questions. He was my teacher, my master, and no one was as useful to me as he was, either by himself or by his books (God bless him and grant him paradise as a reward!). He gave me diplomas in his own handwriting on the subjects he taught, either by his own method or that of others. I communicated to him a number of my works; he put in his hand annotations flattering to me; he even reproduced the results of some of my researches and I heard him quoting some of them in his lessons, which proves his impartiality, his modesty and his respect for the truth in all circumstances. He was with</p>

<note n="1">No doubt the <foreign>c ell paiso</foreign> of Ibn-El-Hadjeb.</note>

<note n="2">This is the <foreign>mon</foreign> of Sidi Khelil.</note>

<note n="3">The ms. C has El-Hadjeb, instead of El-Hadj which is also found in Cherbonneau,</note>

<note n="4">This is the title of the vile sura of the Qur'an.</note>

<note n="5">Ahmed-ben-Yahya-ben-Mohammed ben-Abdelouâhid-ben-Ali-El-Ouancherisi's work of jurisprudence.</note>

<pb n="105"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN</p>

<p>We on the day of our misfortune<ref target="1"/>. That was the last time I saw him. Later I learned that he had died on a Friday of Shaououal in the year 1002 (June-July 1593); he had been born, he had told me, in 930 (1524). He was the author of notes and marginal glosses in which he drew attention to (<foreign>ev</foreign>) the errors committed by the commentators of Khelil and others; he had noted one by one all the errors contained in the great commentary of Et-Tataï, and coming either from the author's own writing or from his quotations. This extremely useful work I have condensed in one of my opuscules (God have mercy on this master!). Here ends the extract I give from the Edz-Dzil<ref target="2"/>.</p>

<p>One of the lords of the people of Sankore, - the fact was transmitted from a reliable source, - had paid an alms of 1000 gold initsqals into the hands of the sheikh, the jurisconsult, the virtuous Abu-Abdallah. i.e., the cadi Moaddib-Mohammed-El-Kâbari; the latter distributed it to the poor at the gate of the mosque of Sankore. Here is what happened: The famine had broken out at that time. The sheikh, speaking one day in his medrasa, said: "Whoever gives an alms of 1000 mitsqals, I will provide him with paradise. It was then that the generous personage in question gave this sum which was distributed among the poor. It is assured that later the sheikh saw in a dream someone who said to him, "In the future do not make any commitments in our name."</p>

<p>As the saint, the ascetic, the jurisconsult Abderrahman, son of the jurisconsult Mahmud, was narrating the previous adventure during his lecture which was held in the mosque, it is said that a man said to him, "O my lord, do you believe

<note n="1">The day Timbuktu was taken by Moroccan troops under the leadership of Djouder.</note>

<note n="2">Cf. the Essay, p. 25.</note>

<pb n="106"/> that at this time if you promised paradise to someone he would give you a thousand mitsqals of gold?" Abderrahman replied with the words, "El-Kâbari and his likes, these are the men who were capable of following such a path."</p>

<p>The sheikh just mentioned, that is, the jurisconsult, the cadi Moaddib-Mohammed-El-Kâbari, the inaître des maîtres (God have mercy on him, show him his satisfaction, and make us enjoy his blessings in this world and the next!) settled in Timbuktu, in the ninth century. He was the contemporary of a great number of sheikhs, among others of the following characters: the jurisconsult Sidi Abderrahman-Et-Temimi, grandfather of the cadi Habib; the jurisconsult Anda-Ag-Mohammed the great, grandfather by his mother of the jurisconsult the cadi Mahmoud; the jurisconsult Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqit, father of the above-mentioned jurisconsult Mahmoud; the very learned one, the pole, Sidi Yahya-Et-Tadelsi, etc. He reached the highest degree of science and virtue. He had for disciples the jurisconsult 'Omar-Anda-Ag-Mohammed-Aqit and Sidi Yahya. It is said that he did not let a single month pass without having the Tehdib<ref target="1"/> of ElBerada i read in full, so many readers did he have. At that time, the city was full of Sudanese students, people from the west (<foreign>EA</foreign>), full of ardor for science and for virtue. It was to such an extent that it is assured that there are, buried in the same enclosure as him, thirty figures of Kabara, all learned and holy. His resting place is between that of the holy jurisconsult El-Hâdj-Ahmed-ben-'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqit and the place where the prayer for rain is made. This is the information provided to us by our master, the ascetic, the jurisconsult, El-Amin-ben-Ahmed, brother of the jurisconsult Abderrahman (may the earth be light to them!).</p>.

<note n="1">This is the <foreign>åblistly as gull Johans wisi</foreign> of Abu-Sa'id-Khelef-ben-Abou-'lQâsem-El-Berâdi'i, a treatise on Malekite law.</note>

<pb n="107"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN 79</p>

<p>This blessed sheikh was the author of many remarkable miracles. Here is one among others: a thaleb from Merrakech gave free rein to his tongue against the sheikh and said unseemly things about him, calling him, for example, El-Kâfiri<ref target="1"/>. This thaleb was highly regarded and enjoyed great credit with the Cherifian princes to whom he read El-Bokhari during Ramadan. God punished him by inflicting him with elephantiasis. Doctors from all over the world were brought in: one of them went so far as to say that the thaleb would only heal as long as it ate the heart of a child. The prince of the time had the throat of who knows how many children slaughtered, but it was of no use and the patient died in sad conditions (God forbid such a fate!). This fact was reported by the very learned, jurisconsult Ahmed-Baba (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>Another miracle is this one that I heard told by my father who had it from his masters: On a certain day of the first ten of dzou-'l-hiddja<ref target="2"/>, the sheikh went out to buy some live animals for the festival of sacrifices. These animals were on the other side of the river. The sheikh, who had one of his disciples with him, started walking on the river. The disciple, driven by some circumstance of which God had the secret, followed the example that was given to him and disappeared in the middle of the river at the moment when his master reached the other bank. The latter then called his disciple, held out his hand and pulled him out of the water; then he said to him, "What has</p>

<note n="1">Play on words on the ethnicity of the character who was El-Kâbari and whom the lhaleb transformed into Kafiri, i.e. "belonging to the infidels". It is only by pronouncing the words in the manner of the vulgar language that the pun is truly possible.</note>

<note n="2"><p>It is on the 10th of this last month of the Muslim year that the great feast, known as the sacrifices, takes place, because on this day the pilgrims have to slit the throat of a victim. On that day all the faithful, wherever they may be, also impolish an animal.</p> <p>Remember! the memory is full of useful teachings; in its folds there is enough to quench the thirst of the elite of those who come to drink;</p> <p>Have you not seen that if the trace of those who put ardor into being generous is worthy of mention, the trace left by the thinkers is even more worthy of estimation. </p> <p>The fragrance of the east wind restores to a man the vigor of the spirit; he then goes to join his companions and help them with his arm<ref target="1"/>;</p> <p>The disappearance of an intelligence from this world is a mourning that is manifested in all countries and in all men of value. </p> <p>The masters of science have been affected by the death of the sheikh, and there is in this event the threat of future misfortunes;</p> <p>O students of the science of law, you know what was among men the one who permeates your hearts with sadness. </p> <p>The sadness that pervades your hearts comes from the loss of that master, that benevolent jurisconsult, bearer of the jewels of science,</p> <p>With perfect teaching, whose intelligence brought everything together and who discovered in the Tehdib the most fortunate indications;</p> <p>That master was Muhammad-Moaddib, the prudent man, whose perseverance and patience constantly raised his rank. </p> <p>Is it possible that after him we will find someone who explains everything?   O Arabs, will we find after him someone to make us walk?   (Whip us).</p> <p>If we did not have for consolation the Prophet, his companions, the great teachers of religion and the spiritual guides,</p> <p>Tears should flow from our eyes like an uninterrupted rain as we see these bodies disappear and these torches extinguished. </p> <p>The world grew dark and its sorrows came to light in that morning when the news of his death spread among the masters.</p></note>

<pb n="108"/>

<p>80 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>so inclined to do so? - As I saw you do, I wanted to do it myself too, replied the other. - How could you compare your foot with that of a man who never walked in the way of divine disobedience!" cried the sheikb.</p> <p>

<p>On the day when this sheikh died (God have mercy on him!), the sheikh, the imam, the saint, the enlightened one, the model, the seer, the pole, the helper, the scholar, the well-directed one, the noble lord, the divine Sidi Yahya-Et-Tadelsi made his elegy in the following verses (<foreign>vv</foreign>):</p>



<note n="1">The text of these verses being often altered by copyists, the translation is sometimes doubtful.</note>

<pb n="109"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN</p>

<p>What clever man would refuse to come and carry it into the ground with the crowd? The elders, too, had the sorrow of these harsh trials,</p> <p>

<p>When the two stretchers broke under a righteous man who had led us to Medina more than once<ref target="1"/>,</p>

<p>By doing this we will be honoring and doing an act of good education to the righteous man who was faithful to the pact of maitress<ref target="2"/>.</p>

<p>O my brethren, pray for him; may God make him welcome by granting him the rest and quiet of a glorious grave!</p>

<p>May he enjoy a wide abode in paradise as a testimony to his mastery and as a prize for his submission to the faith!</p>

<p>May he receive from the Clement, to whom belong the glory and sublimity, a salvation full of benevolence and happy profit;</p>

<p>May the Lord, the God of the throne, deign to shower his blessings on the best of his envoys, his most eminent representative,</p>

<p>Mahomet, who has been chosen to complete the work of mercy and complete the task of his noble predecessors;</p>

<p>May it be so also for his family, his companions, and their successors, all those for whose sake the prayer of the faithful is raised! (<foreign>0.</foreign>).</p>

<p>Such is this piece of verse which I have copied from a text written in my father's hand (God, by his grace, have mercy on him and forgive him!).</p>

<p>Genealogy of Sheikh Sidi Yahya (God have mercy on him, make us enjoy his blessings and send them back to us in this world and the next! ) His name was Yahia - ben-Abderrahim-ben-Abderrahman-EtsTsa'alebi-ben-Yahia-El-Bekkaï-ben-Abou'l-Hasan- 'Ali-ben-Abdallah-ben-Abdeldjebbâr-ben-Temimben-Hormoz-ben-Hâtem-ben-Qosaï-ben - Youcefben- Youch'a-ben-Ouard-ben-Battâl-ben-Ahmedben-Mohammed-ben-Aïssa-ben-Mohammed-benEl-Hasan-ben-'Ali-ben-Abou-Tâleb (God whiten the face of the latter and show his satisfaction and mercy to all! ). He came to Timbuktu at the beginning of the government of the Tuareg;he was well received there by the Timbuktu-</p>

<note n="1">Uncertain translation.</p> <p>

<note n="2">This last word is far from certain.</note>



<pb n="110"/>

<p>82 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>Koi, Mohammed-Naddi, who took a liking to him, treated him with the utmost distinction, and had a mosque built for him and entrusted him with the duties of imam.</p>

<p>Yahya reached the highest degree of knowledge, virtue and holiness; his fame spread through all countries and throughout the universe. His blessings were felt by all great and small. He performed many miracles and often had double vision. The jurisconsult, the cadi, the father of blessings, Mahmoud said: Of all those who set foot in Timbuktu, no one was as eminent as Sidi Yahya. The saint, the ascetic, the jurisconsult, the preacher Abu-Zeid-Abderrahman, son of the jurisconsult Mahmud, who has just been appointed, said in turn: 'It is the duty of the people of Timbuktu to visit the mausoleum of Sidi Yahya every day to obtain its blessings, and they should do so even if they were to remain three days' walk from this city<ref target="1"/>.'</p>

<p>All in his early days (God have mercy on him!) Sidi Yahya refrained from trading; but at the end of his career, he actively engaged in it. He told about this subject that until the time of giving himself up to trading he saw the Prophet every night in a dream; then he saw him only once a week, then once a month and finally once a year. And when he was asked about the reason for this, he said, "I suppose it is only because of my business. - And why don't you give it up? - He said, "I don't want to be dependent on anyone. See (God have mercy on you and us!) how fatal trading is, although this blessed sheikh took the greatest care and put the greatest scruple in guarding against everything</p>

<note n="1">The distance of three days' walk is considered, among Muslims, to be a sufficient distance to dispense with certain obligations of a religious or legal nature.</p> <pb

<pb n="111"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN 83</p>

<p>that which is unlawful. See, too, how hard is the necessity of being dependent on others, since, because of this (<foreign>01</foreign>), this blessed master renounced a high divine favor. We ask God to give us the grace to be forgiving and indulgent in this world and in the next!</p>

<p>It is said that one day, surrounded by a group of students, and sitting outside the mosque at the foot of the minaret, he was giving his lecture, when the clouds rising in the sky threatened a rain so soon, that the students were preparing to get up. Then the thunder rumbled, and the sheikh said, "Don't hurry, stay put, for the rain will not fall here, the angel orders it to go to such and such a country." And indeed the clouds passed and disappeared.</p>

<p>Our master, the ascetic, the jurisconsult, El-Amin-benAhmed (God have mercy on him!) told us that one day the sheikh's maids had put a fresh fish to cook and had left it from morning till evening without the fire producing the slightest effect. As he heard them wonder at this, he said to them, "My foot touched something wet as I passed through the vestibule on my way to prayer this morning, perhaps it was the fish that it brushed against: now fire cannot burn anything that my body has touched."</p>

<p>It is also said that when the students of Sankore came to him to receive his lessons, he would say to them, "O people of Sankore, you should be satisfied with Sidi Abderrahman-Et-Temimi." This character had come from the Hedjaz in the company of Sultan Mousa, king of Melli, when the latter returned from his pilgrimage to Mecca. He settled in Timbuktu and found this city filled with a crowd of Sudanese jurisconsults. As soon as he realized that they knew more about law than he did, he left for Fez, devoted himself to the study of law there, and then returned to settle</p>

<pb n="112"/>

<p>84 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>again in Timbuktu. He was the grandfather of Cadi Habib (God have mercy on them all!).</p>

<p>In the year 868 (1463-1464) Sidi Yahya died and shortly after him died his friend Sheikh Mohammed-Naddi, as said before (God have mercy on them both!).</p>

<p>Sheikh Masira-Bobo-Ez-Zoghrâni, friend of the jurisconsult Mahmud-ben-'Omar. - He was an eminent theologian, a good, virtuous, pious man. His tribe is not known for its virtue or for the purity of its Islam. In his early days, the preacher, the ascetic, the jurisconsult Abderrahman, son of the jurisconsult Mahmud, was assiduous with him (<foreign>or</foreign>); he allowed himself to be led by him and collected a number of his sermons. It is said that one day while he was in his medrasa he was told of a funeral. Who is it?" he asked - "A Zoghrâni," he was told. - So," he continued, "I want to go and pray over him in consideration of Sheikh Masira-Bobo. He indeed went to the funeral and prayed over the deceased there.</p>

<p>The sheikh, the scholar in God, the saint, the man gifted with double sight, the author of miracles, the jurisconsult AbuAbdallah-Mohammed -ben-Mohammed-ben-Aliben-Mousa, 'Oriân-er-râs (Bare Head). He was one of the virtuous servants of God, a generous ascetic who spent all his wealth in alms for the sake of God. When he received offerings or gifts, he kept none for himself and gave them to the poor and needy. He bought a large number of slaves and then gave them their freedom for the love of God and for the future life. He had no doorkeeper; everyone entered his house without asking permission. People came to visit him from all countries and at all hours, especially on Fridays after the asr prayer.</p>

<pb n="113"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN 85</p>

<p>The people who visited him most often were the people of the Makhzen<ref target="1"/>, pashas, lesser personages, and travelers passing through; they made these visits to him because of his many blessings, Sometimes he was expansive, sometimes, on the contrary, he was concentrated. In his expansive moments he would tell those around him strange or wonderful stories; he would laugh at the very first of his stories. Sometimes, when he was laughing, he would strike the hand of his interlocutor with his blessed hand and put his left hand over his mouth. He often hit me on the hand in this way. When, on the other hand, he was concentrating, he did not say anything and was content to answer the person who was speaking to him. In these moments, what I heard him say most often were these phrases: "What God wants will be; what he does not want will not be. Or again: "God is my support and he is enough for me", that God hears whoever implores him", "there is nothing beyond God". If someone, having experienced some misfortune, asked him to recite the Fatiha<ref target="2"/>, he would extend his two blessed hands and after saying the formula of exorcisin<ref target="3"/> and the bismillah<ref target="4"/> he would say: Ya sin, etc.<ref target="5"/>; O most merciful of the merciful, O most merciful of the merciful, O most merciful of the merciful. Then he recited the Fatiha three times and made the following invocation three times: May God improve us and you, may He restore our affairs and yours (<foreign>or</foreign>), may He provide you and us with a calm and happy end.</p>

<p>It was not until near the end of his life, when the moment</p>

<note n="1">The word "Makhzen" is used in Morocco and Sudan to refer to the government or court of the ruler.</p> <p>

<note n="2">The first chapter of the Qur'an.</p> <p>

<note n="3">The last sura of the Qur'an.</note>

<note n="4">The formula of saying, "In the name of God the merciful, the gracious," which one must say whenever one undertakes something.</note>

<note n="5">This is the title and the beginning of the thirty-sixth sura of the Qur'an.</note>

<pb n="114"/>

<p>86 HISTORY OF SUDAN</p>

<p>of the supreme journey approached, that he had a doorkeeper and no longer allowed entry to his house as in the early days. Sometimes he even refused to receive at certain times. From that time on he only recited the Fatiha once, and then he stopped reciting it. One day when I was sitting in front of him, he said to me: "To all those who will come here, tell them that I cannot recite this Fatiha anymore. He then performed his customary prayer for me only once and it was the last one (God have mercy on him, show him satisfaction and place him in the highest degree of the final abode!)</p>.

<p>At the beginning of his career, he met the father of generous works, the saint, the pole, the scholar, Sidi Mohammed-El-Bekri, a very young man at that time. As he had just left his friend in God, the jurisconsult Ahmed-ben-El-Hâdj -Ahmed-ben-'Omar-ben-MohammedAqit, following one of the customary visits that they made between them, he found the young man sitting at noon near the door of the mosque of Sankoré, whose door was not yet open; El-Bekri was holding in his hand the book of the Risala of Abou-Zeïd-El-Qaïrouâni which he was studying under the direction of his master the jurisconsult Abderrahman, son of the jurisconsult Mahmoud. On seeing him, the blessed sheikh stopped and asked him what book he was holding in his hand: "This is the Risala," answered El-Bekri. The sheikh held out his blessed hand and said, "Show it to me. Then taking it in his hands, he examined it for a moment and handed it back saying, "God bless you about this book<ref target="1"/>." Then he passed on his way, not knowing who he had been dealing with, for he had never seen him. When his master returned to the mosque, he told him about this adventure and the master suspected that it was El-Bekri. On leaving the mosque</p>

<note n="1">That is, "May you benefit from this work."</note>

<pb n="115"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN</p>

<p>he went to his brother, the jurisconsult Ahined, who has just been mentioned, and said to him, "Has Sidi Mohammed-El-Bekri come to see you today? - Yes," answered Ahmed, "he even stayed later than usual. Then the master told him what had happened between El-Bekri and Mohammed-Ad<ref target="1"/>-'Ali-Mousa, as the people of Sankore called him.</p>

<p>Later on the sheikh's mind became so troubled that it was thought that he had gone mad. He only slept in mosques (or the mosque) anymore. Mohammed-El-Bekri heard that the sheikh had announced that he had seen the One who cannot be seen<ref target="2"/>: and that therefore his end would be happy. Now, one of his trustworthy students told me that he had asked the sheikh if anyone in this world had seen God. Yes," he replied, "there is a person in this city who has seen God the Most High at the same time as you. As (08) I was talking about this fact to my master, the most learned, the jurisconsult Mohammed-Baba, the son of the jurisconsult El-Amin, without telling him who had spoken these words, my master said to me, "The one who said this is the very one who has seen the Lord (may he be blessed and exalted!)."</p>

<p>On a certain Friday, after the asr prayer, there were three of us with the sheikh, me and two others. The sheikh was in one of his expansive moments and he was chatting with us. Suddenly the clouds rose in the sky. Immediately changing his face, the sheikh became sullen, interrupted his conversation and remained extremely agitated in his classroom. Hardly had the first</p>

<note n="1">Presumably equivalent or abbreviation of Aida "they."</p> <p>

<note n="2">The preceding part of the sentence was missing in mss. A and B. It is also missing in the printed text; ms, C was not yet in my possession when the printing of this part of the text was taking place. The one who cannot be seen is God. According to Muslims, no man can see God without dying immediately afterwards; there was no exception except for Moses.</p> <p>The only exception was Moses.

<pb n="116"/>

<p>88 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>drops of rain fell that he became harsh and violent in his speech. "I don't want to receive anyone," he said, "when the rain falls." We all went out at once. I told the adventure to my master, the jurisconsult El-Amin, and he was quite surprised.</p>

<p>One of my confreres told me the following fact: "I had a neighbor with whom, morning and evening, we used to meet in intimacy. One day he missed the appointment and, as his house was next to mine, I went to his house to ask about him. When I reached the door of his house, the porter went to warn him, then returned and said to me: "My master informs you that he cannot see you at this moment. When I heard this, I almost burst out in anger, and beating my chest with my hand, I cried out, "A man like me goes to visit such a man in his home and he sends him away without even seeing him! I decided from then on never to speak to him again.</p>.

<p>Not long after that, I visited the blessed sheikh. Sidi Mohammed-'Oriân-er-râs. No sooner had I entered his presence than, after greeting me, he spoke to me in these terms:</p> <p>"One of the saints of God had lost one of the situations he occupied. He was so grieved that he wished to meet El-Khidr<ref target="1"/> (greetings be upon him!) so that he could intercede with God to get him to return the position he had lost. God, in His kindness and grace, restored it to him without the intercession of anyone. Shortly afterwards ElKhidr came to the saint and greeted him at the door of his house: "Who are you, said the saint? - I am the person you asked for," said El-Khidr. - God has made it possible for me to do without you," said the saint. El-Khidr went away, without beating his chest with his hand and without saying, "O such a one, one does not</p>

<note n="1">El-Khidr is the character referred to in the Qur'an, Sura xviii verses 62ff.</p> <pb

<pb n="117"/>

<p>CHAPTER TEN 89</p>

<p>"send back not such a man as I". The man was excusable, for he was undoubtedly in a position where he could not be seen by anyone." I understood then what he meant; I repented of what I had done; I asked God's forgiveness and went to find my neighbor and confrere. I introduced myself and he immediately had me open his door. I entered and he said to me, "Excuse me for not letting myself be seen on the day you came, but I was lying (<foreign>oo</foreign>) on the floor at the time and had colic. I couldn't admit that anyone saw me in that state. - God forgive you and me," I replied.</p>.

<p>One of his neighbors related the following fact: I had gone one day to the cadi Mahmoud-ben-Ahmed-ben-Abderrahman: 'You have a saint for a neighbor,' he said to me. - Yes," I answered. - The saint who does not come to the Friday service," he added. I kept silent, then after that I went to see my neighbor Sidi Mohammed- Oriân-er-râs. O such a one," he said to me, "should one forgive or not? - Forgiveness is better," I answered. - Indeed, he replied, if I did not forgive, things would happen that would not be appropriate. Well, tell the one who claims that I do not go to the Friday prayer that, long before he came to the service, he was preceded by the one he claims never to have attended. Anecdotes of this kind on his account are extremely numerous (God have mercy on him, show him satisfaction and let us enjoy his influence! Amen!)</p>

<p>The jurisconsult, the theologian, the ascetic, the virtuous, the pious, the reserved, our master El-Amin-ben-Ahmed, the uterine brother of the jurisconsult Abderrahman-ben-Ahmed, the head of the school. His tongue unceasingly moistened to proclaim the praises of God, so Sidi Mohammed-'Oriảner-râs did not call him otherwise than El-Amin the litanist.</p>.

<pb n="118"/>

<p>90 SUDAN HISTORY</p>

<p>One of my confreres from the people of Sankore told me that his father, a very old man, had said to him, "I knew Sankore in the old days when the virtuous people were very numerous there, well, I have not seen any of them practicing Islam with as much fervor as the jurisconsult El-Amin."</p>

<p>He told us, himself (may God have mercy on him! ) in his medrasa, that the jurisconsult 'Omar-benMohammed-ben-'Omar, brother of the jurisconsult Ahmed-Moghya, was studying the Shifa of the cadi Iyâd under the guidance of the very learned, the erudite, the jurisconsult Ahmed-ben-El-HâdjAbmed-ben-'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqit and that he and his son the jurisconsult Ahmed-Baba attended his lessons, as well as the jurisconsult, cadi Ahmed (<foreign>04</foreign>). The master did not allow anyone to ask him a question; he made an exception only for the student being questioned and, at certain times, for Sidi Ahmed. As for his son AhmedBaba, each time he asked a question, his father told him: "Shut up! One day, however, when the teacher had asked the student 'Omar whether the verb qabuha is transitive or intransitive, the latter could not answer, so he turned to Sidi Ahmed, who also kept silent. "However," he said, "I have read to you this verse: and they will be ashamed<ref target="1"/> (s. XXVIII, v. 42)."</p>As he said this, he turned his eyes towards me and began to smile.</p>

<p>We were a number of fellow students who one day showed our sheikh, the jurisconsult El-Amin, the book entitled: Delail el-kheïrát<ref target="2"/>, the copies of which have variants, and we asked him to tell us whether the word seyyidna should be retained or rejected. He replied: We addressed the same question to our</p>

<note n="1">The word translated as "disgraced" is the past participle of the verb about which he was questioning. There is an untranslatable pun.</p> <note>

<note n="2">The title of a book of prayers and litanies in honor of the Prophet. Its author is Mohammed-ben-Soliman-El-Djezouli.</note>


<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12"><head>CHAPTER XII: <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName></head>

<p>
As for that master tyrant, that famous villain, <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>, whose name is written with an o placed after the s and an i after the redoubled n, according to the spelling I found fixed in the <title>Dzeil ed-dibâdj</title> of the very learned jurisconsult <persName>Ahmed-Baba</persName> (God most-holy be merciful to him!), he was a man gifted with great strength and powerful energy.
Wicked, libertine, unjust, oppressor, bloodthirsty, he killed so many men that God alone knows the number. He persecuted the learned and the pious by attacking their lives, their honor or their consideration.
</p>
<p>
Speaking about the main events of the ninth century, the very learned, the scholar, <persName>El-'Alyami</persName> (God have mercy on him!) expresses himself as follows in the commentary of the work of <persName>El-Djelâl-Es-Soyouti, entitled El-Djami-es-ser'irt</persName>: <quote>We
<note n="1">The full title of this work relating to Muslim traditions is:

<foreign xml:lang="ara">الجامع الصغير من حديث البشير النذير</foreign>
The commentary referred to is that of <persName>Shems-ed-Dîn-Mohammed-Ei-'Alqami</persName>.</note>
<pb n="104"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="132"/>


 have learned that there appeared in the country of Tekrour, under the name of <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>, a character who causes men to perish and ravages the land. This character began to reign in the year 869<ref target="104.1"/> (1464-1465).</quote></p>

 <p>It is reported that the father of blessings, the saint of God, <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>, <persName><roleName>the cadi</roleName>  <persName>Mahmud</persName>-ben-'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqît</persName>, was born one year before the advent of <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>. This is true. Indeed, I have seen in the <title>Dzeil</title>2 that <persName> <persName>Mahmud</persName></persName> (God have mercy on him!) was born in the year 868 and that he died in the year 955 on Thursday evening, the 16th of the month of Ramadan (October 19, 1548).
</p>
<p>
<persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> occupied the throne twenty-seven or twenty-eight years.
His reign was employed in warlike expeditions and conquests of countries. He seized <placeName>Dienné</placeName>, where he stayed for a year and a month. He conquered <placeName>Djondjo</placeName> and allowed the <roleName><placeName>Dirma</placeName>-koï</roleName>3 to enter it on horseback on several occasions. Only the two of them enjoyed this favor which belonged exclusively to the prince of <placeName>Songhaï</placeName>.4 </p>
<p>
He also conquered <placeName>Bara</placeName> and <placeName>the territory of the <rs type="ethnic">Senhâdja-Nounou</rs></placeName>, which at that time was ruled by Queen Bikoun-Kâbi. He took <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName> and all the mountains, except <placeName>Domqui</placeName>, which resisted him. He conquered the country of <rs type="ethnic">the Kounta</rs> and intended to inflict the same fate on the country
<note n="1">866, according to ms. C, which, according to what follows, is surely a copyist's error.</note>
<note n="2">The <title>Dzeil-ed-Dibâdj</title> of <persName>Ahmed-Baba</persName>, already cited above.</note>

<note n="3">This is probably a title of work: the head of <placeName>Dirma</placeName>.</note>

<note n="4">The text does not specify the town into which the <roleName><placeName>Dirma</placeName>-koï</roleName> had the right to enter on horseback, but it does seem to apply to the town of <placeName>Djondjo</placeName>.</note>

<note n="5">The author writes: "the mountains," presumably to mean the mountainous countries of which the country of <placeName>Dom</placeName> or <placeName>Doum</placeName> was a part.</note>

<note n="6">The <rs type="ethnic">Kounta tribe</rs> is a large <rs type="ethnic">Moorish tribe</rs> of the so-called <placeName>Sahel region</placeName>; its very vast territory extends northwest of <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName> and borders the Adrar country (cf. the Notice sur les Maures du Sénégal et du Soudan, by Commander R. de Lartigue, in the Bulletin du Comité de l'Afrique française, supplement of July 1897).</note>
<pb n="105"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="133"/>

 of <placeName>Bergou</placeName>,1 but he could not succeed. His last expedition was directed against the country of <placeName>Gourma</placeName>.2 </p>

<p>
As soon as <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> was invested with sovereign authority, the <roleName><placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>-Koï</roleName>, <persName>Sheikh Mohammed-Naddi</persName>, sent him a letter of greetin and good-wishes. In this letter he asked the prince not to take away his money, as he considered himself one of the prince's family members.</p>

<p>
Upon his death, the sheikh was replaced in his duties by his son <persName>'Omar</persName>. The latter in turn wrote a letter which was the very opposite of the one his father had addressed to the prince. In this letter, he said that his father had left this world with nothing but two pieces of linen. As for him, he added, he had many forces at his disposal (<ref target="arpage65">٦٥</ref>) and all those who would obstruct him would see what those forces were.</p>

<p>
On receiving this letter, <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> said to his companions:
<q>What a difference between the spirit of this young man and that of his father! The gap that arises between their speeches is equal to that between their minds.</q></p>

<p>
<persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> entered <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName> on the 4th or 5th of the month of redjeb in the year 873 (29 or 30 January 1468), the fourth or fifth year of his accession to the throne. He exercised in this city great, immense and terrible destruction; he set it on fire, ruined it and caused the death of a great number of people.</p> 

<p>
As soon as Akil had heard of the coming of <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>,

<note n="1">Or <placeName>Berkou</placeName>.</note>

<note n="2">Or <foreign>Korma</foreign>. This probably refers to <placeName>the country of Gourma</placeName> which is in <placeName>the loop of the Niger</placeName>.</note>

<note n="3">I have adopted the reading from ms. C which replaces <foreign xml:lang="ara">باله</foreign> with <foreign xml:lang="ara">ماله</foreign>. It is impossible to retain the reading of the printed text, even assuming that the sheikh was asking not to send his children as hostages to the court because he considered himself part of the prince's family.</note>
<pb n="106"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="134"/>


he had brought a thousand camels and, taking with him <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>s of <placeName>Sankore</placeName>, for their fate was what concerned him most, he had set out for <placeName>Biro</placeName>. In this exodus were <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> 'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqit</persName>, and his three blessed children: <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Abdallah</persName>, <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Ahmed</persName> who was the eldest of the three, and <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>  <persName>Mahmud</persName></persName> who was the youngest. The latter, at that time, was a child of five years old, unable to stand on a mount or to walk on foot. He had to be carried on his shoulders and it was <persName>Makkanki</persName>'s grandfather, one of their slaves, who had to carry the burden until the arrival in <placeName>Biro</placeName>. In the group of those who made this journey was the maternal uncle of these young men, <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> El-Mokhtar, the grammarian, son of <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Anda-Ag-Mohammed who knew Imam Ez-Zemmouri
(God have mercy on him!) in <placeName>Biro</placeName> and obtained from him the diploma for teaching the book of <title>Ech-Chifa</title> from <persName><roleName>the cadi</roleName> 'Iyâd</persName> (God have mercy on him!).</p>

<p>
On the day of departure, one saw middle-aged men, all bearded, trembling with fear when it came to riding a camel, and then falling to the ground as soon as the animal got up. It is because our virtuous ancestors kept their children in their bosom, so that these children grew up without knowing anything about life, because, being young, they had never played. Now, play at this time, forms the man and teaches him a great number of things. The parents then regretted having done so, and when they were back in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>, they gave their children time to play and relaxed from the restraint they had imposed on them.</p>

<p>
The tyrant, the libertine,1 hastened to kill or humiliate

<note n="1">The author often uses these two epithets to refer to <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>.</note>
<pb n="107"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="135"/>
 
 all the scholars who had remained in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>.
He gave the pretext that they were the friends of <rs type="ethnic">the Tuareg</rs>, indeed members of their elite, and that this was why he was angry with them. He had the mother of <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Mohammed imprisoned, who was <persName>Sata</persName>1, the daughter of <persName>Anda-Ag-Mohammed</persName> (<ref target="arpage66">٦٦</ref>), and he had the two brothers of this lady, <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>  <persName>Mahmud</persName></persName> and <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Ahmed</persName>, both sons of <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Anda-Ag-Mohammed</persName>, put to death. In short, he did not cease to inflict misery upon misery, humiliation upon humiliation
to all the scholars (God preserve us from such a fate!).</p>

<p>
One day he gave orders to bring to him, to make them his concubines, thirty virgins, daughters of scholars. He was then at the port of <placeName>Kabara</placeName> and wanted these girls to make the journey on foot. So they set out, leaving the women's quarters for the first time2. A servant of the prince accompanied them; he made them walk until, having arrived at a certain place, they were absolutely unable to go any further. The servant informed the prince, who ordered them all to be put to death, which was done (Heaven forbid!). The place where they had stopped is located to the west and very close to <placeName>Amadagha</placeName> and is called:<placeName xml:lang="xara">Fina qadar el-abkâr</placeName>3.</p>

<p>
After the departure of the scholars for <placeName>Biro</placeName>, <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> invested <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>, <roleName>cadi</roleName> Habîb</persName>, grandson of <persName><roleName>the seyyid</roleName> Abderrahmân-Et-Temîmi</persName>, with the duties of <roleName>cadi</roleName>, and he had the greatest regard for the paternal cousin of this <roleName>cadi</roleName>, <persName>El-Mamoun</persName>, father of <persName>'Ammâr-Ida-El-Mamoun</persName>. It was to the point that he only called him <q>my father</q> 4. Also, when the prince

 <note n="1">Or <foreign>Sita</foreign>.</note>

<note n="2">Girls very rarely go out among Muslims in the cities, so they are not very used to walking.</note>

<note n="3">That is, <gloss>the threshold of the virgins' fate,</gloss> or, perhaps, with a different vocalization, <gloss>the limit of the virgins' power.</gloss></note>

<note n="4">In conversation Arabs often address each other with expressions such as: 'my cousin', 'my brother', 'my uncle', 'my son', 'my father'. This last formula always marks great deference.</note>
<pb n="108"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="136"/>


 was dead and everyone began to tell of his misdeeds, El-Mamoun always repeated, <q>I will say no evil of <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>; he has always been good to me; never has he acted badly towards me, as he has done towards others.</q> So he said neither good nor bad about him, and this just attitude earned him the consideration of the father of blessings, <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>  Mahmud</persName>.</p>

<p>Until the year 875 (1470-1471), <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> continued to have scholars put to death or humiliated. Also all those of the people of <placeName>Sankore</placeName> who had remained in the city also fled to <placeName>Biro</placeName>. The prince sent the <persName><roleName><placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>-Koï</roleName>, El-Mokhtår-Mohammed-ben-Naddi</persName>, to pursue the fugitives. The latter caught up with them at <placeName>Ta'djit</placeName>1 where a fight took place in which the most eminent of them were killed. This affair of <placeName>Ta'djit</placeName> is well known.</p>

<p>
Then turning against the children of <persName><roleName>the cadi</roleName> El-Hay</persName>2 who were in <placeName>Alfa'a-Konko</placeName>3, the prince inflicted on them all sorts of insults and humiliations. Many of them then took refuge in <placeName>Tikda</placeName>. <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> then declared that these people had gone to this region to appeal to <rs type="ethnic">the Tuareg</rs> and ask them to come and avenge them from him. He immediately gave the order to massacre all those who who had remained in <placeName>Alfa'a-Konko</placeName> and, after having killed a large number of them, he had the rest imprisoned, men and women (God forbid!). It was because of this, it is said, that from that time to this day the rain did not fall in that place in sufficient quantity to be useful.</p>

<p>
Thirty men, from among the most prominent, fled from that city and went west (<ref target="arpage67">٦٧</ref>). A certain

<note n="1">Or <placeName>Ta'djit</placeName>i.</note>

<note n="2">Or <foreign>El-Hayy</foreign>.</note>

<note n="3">The ms. C says: <foreign>Alfagha</foreign>. It seems that it is rather the word <foreign>Alfa'a</foreign> which means.
<gloss>literate</gloss>, <gloss>scholar</gloss>, <gloss>marabout</gloss>.</note>
<pb n="109"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="137"/>


 day, that in the course of their flight they had arrived at the town of <placeName>Chibi</placeName>, they settled down under a tree to take a nap; they had not eaten anything since the day before and fell asleep. One of them soon awoke and said to his companions:
<q>I have just seen us all in a dream breaking our fast this very night in paradise.</q> No sooner had he finished these words than horsemen sent by the perfidious, the scoundrel, arrived and put them all to death (God forbid! may he show mercy to all these characters and show them his satisfaction!)</p>

<p>
On a certain day, in order to affront and torture him, the prince forced <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> <persName>Ibrahim</persName>, <roleName>chief of <placeName>Alfa'a-Konko</placeName></roleName></persName>, and son of <persName>Abu-Bekr</persName>, son of <persName><roleName>the cadi</roleName> El-Hay</persName>, to remain in the sunlight in that place. The prince then saw in a dream <persName>Ibrahim</persName>'s father, <persName>Abu-Bekr</persName>, who was beating him vigorously with his stick, saying, <q>May God scatter your children as you have scattered mine!</q> This wish was granted.</p>

<p>
As for the people of <placeName>Alfa'a-Konko</placeName> who had taken refuge in <placeName>Tikda</placeName>, they remained there and made that city their new home.</p>

<p>Despite all these persecutions he made the scholars endure, <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> nevertheless recognized their merits.
<q>Without the scholars,</q> he said, <q>there would be in this world neither pleasure nor enjoyment.</q> And indeed, he did good to a number of them and treated them with respect. Thus, when he made an expedition against the <rs type="ethnic">Fulani</rs>1 and raided the tribe of <rs type="ethnic">Sonfotir</rs>, he sent a great number of captive women to the notables of <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>, some to the scholars and saints as gifts, and he enjoined them all to make them their concubines. Those who did not observe the duties of religion did indeed make them their concubines, but the

<note n="1">The <rs type="ethnic">Fulani</rs> or <rs type="ethnic">Foulbés</rs>.</note>
<pb n="110"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="138"/>
 

men who faithfully follow its precepts married them.</p>

<p>
Among these was the grandfather of my paternal grandmother, <persName><roleName>the eminent seyyid</roleName>, <roleName>the good man</roleName>, <roleName>the ascetic</roleName>, <roleName>Imam</roleName> Abdallah-El-Belbâli</persName>; he married the woman who had been sent to him and whose name was <persName>'<persName>Aisha</persName>-El-Fulâniya</persName>1. It is from this marriage that <persName>Nâna-Bir-Touri</persName>, the mother of my father's mother, was born. My father was still able to know this <persName>Aisha</persName>; she was extremely old and blind.</p>

<p>Among the traits of character of this libertine tyrant, one must mention the way he played with religion. He would postpone his five daily prayers until the night or the next day, and then he would gesture repeatedly while sitting down and calling each prayer by name2. After which he would make a single final greeting and say, <q>Now divide all this among yourselves, since you know each other well.</q></p>


<p>Another feature of his character was that he would give orders to kill someone, even one of the people he esteemed most, without the slightest motive or (<ref target="arpage68">٦٨</ref>) necessity.
Sometimes he repented of what he had done. So, knowing this, his servants hid and sheltered all those whose murder he had ordered to be repented of. As soon as this repentance appeared they said to him, <q>We have spared him, he is not dead.</q> He was then very happy about this circumstance.</p>

<p>One of his servants <persName>Askia-Mohammed</persName> often acts in this way.

<note n="1">'<persName>Aisha</persName>, the Fulbright.</note>

<note n="2">Instead of doing, for example, the morning prayer at the canonical time, he would do it in the evening at the same time as others, merely saying, "This is the morning prayer, this is the noon prayer, etc." Also to save time he would make the final salutation that ends each prayer only once for the cing prayers.</note>
<pb n="111"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="139"/>
 
How many times having received the order to put someone
death or to imprison him, he did the opposite of what he had been told. This <persName>Askia-Mohammed</persName> acted in this way because he was very energetic and very brave; God had put this energy in his temperament. When it happened to him to be in the face of the violence of the prince, his mother <persName>Kasaï</persName> went to <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName> to find <persName>Nâna-Tinti</persName>, the daughter of <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Abou-Bekr, son of <persName><roleName>the cadi</roleName> El-Hay</persName>; she asked her to pray for God to help her son against <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>.
<q>If God,</q> she said, <q>answers your prayer, he will grant you, if he pleases, all the joys in your children and in your relatives.</q> This promise was fulfilled when he came to power.</p>

<p>
As for <roleName>Askia</roleName>'s brother, <persName>'Omar-Komzâgho</persName>, he was very docile to the prince's orders, for he was an intelligent and fine man; so the tyrant never caused him the slightest trouble, unlike what he did to his <persName><roleName>secretary</roleName> <persName>Ibrahim</persName>-El-Khidr</persName>. This secretary, originally from <persName>Fez</persName>, had come to settle in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName> and lived in the neighborhood of the great mosque on the south side pulling a little to the west. <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>, who had given him the functions of secretary, gave an order one day to put him to death and to confiscate all his goods. The order was only partly carried out1, for the servants of the prince hid <persName>Ibrahim</persName>. This remained the case until the day when the prince received the book of <title>Risala</title>2. And when he had no one with him who could read it, he cried out, <q>Oh, if <persName>Ibrahim</persName>, the windbag, were here, we should not be in the trouble we are in because of this book!</q> - <q><persName>Ibrahim</persName> is alive,</q> he was told,

<note n="1">The text says: <gloss>the order was carried out,</gloss> without saying in part what the rest indicates.</note>

<note n="2">This anecdote seems to be intended to show that there were no more scholars in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>, since no one was able to read this work of law called the <title>Risala</title>.</note>
<pb n="112"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="140"/>

 <q>because we hid him.</q> The prince gave the order to bring <persName>Ibrahim</persName>. The latter read the book and was reinstated in his duties. He also received double the money he had lost. In spite of this, he found peace and rest only during the reign of <persName>Askia-Mohammed</persName> who confirmed him in his functions, honored him and treated him generously until the day he died. <persName>Hauïa</persName>1, <persName>Ibrahim</persName>'s son, succeeded his father as secretary, but was attached in this capacity to the person of the inspector appointed by <roleName>Askia</roleName> in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>. This new position was honorable and of great importance.</p>

<p>
<persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> entered <placeName>Kabara</placeName> in the year 882 (1477); it was in this same year that the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName>3 entered
Sâma. In 884 (1479) <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> was in <roleName>Tosoko</roleName>. In the same year <persName>Aïda-Hamed</persName> was born, son of the sister of <persName>Alfa- <persName>Mahmud</persName></persName>4. As for  <persName>Mahmud</persName> (God have mercy on him!) he fasted for the first time that year too (<ref target="arpage69">٦٩</ref>). He related that he was then, if I am wrong, seventeen years old, and that he left <placeName>Kabara</placeName> in the year 885 (1480) <note n="6"/>.</p>

<p>In that year in the month of djomâda I (9 July-8 August
1480) the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName> entered <placeName>Biro</placeName> which he left in djomada II
(8 August-7 September 1480); the siege had lasted one month. He demanded from the inhabitants that they give him a wife and he married the daughter of the eminent <persName><roleName>seyyid</roleName> Anda-Naddi-'Ali-benAbou-Bekr</persName>7. He kept her until the advent of the prince of the believers <persName><roleName>Askia</roleName> El-Hâdj-Mohammed</persName>. It was this prince who 



<note n="1">Or <foreign>Houïa</foreign>.</note>

<note n="2">It was a way of controller of the local administration.</note>

<note n="3">The text simply bears Mouchi, which is for <placeName>Mossi</placeName>; but Mouchi-Koi is found a little further on.</note>

<note n="4">The word Alfa' here has the value of "scholar."</note>

<note n="5">It is often by the time he first jedne that a Muslim knows approximately the date of his birth.</note>

<note n="6">Ms. C says: 805.</note>

<note n="7">This passage in the printed text contains the displacement of a phrase that makes it unintelligible.</note>
<pb n="113"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="141"/>

 delivered this woman from the hands of the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName> after having made war on him and sacked the city; then he married this woman
in his turn. After the siege, the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName> fought against the inhabitants of <placeName>Biro</placeName>, defeated them and took their families captive. But, as he was returning with his booty, the inhabitants of <placeName>Biro</placeName> pursued him, fought him and delivered their captive families. <persName>Omar-ben-Mohammed-Naddi</persName>, who at that time was in <placeName>Biro</placeName>, made himself known by his valour and his ardour in battle. He was the first to reach the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName>1 and knew how to force him to deliver the families that he was taking captive.</p>

<p>
In the month of Sha'aban of this year (October 8-November 7, 1480) <persName>Alfa'-Mahmud</persName> left <placeName>Biro</placeName> and returned to <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>. He related (God have mercy on him!) that he then studied the <title>Risâla</title> of <persName>Ibn-Abou-Zeid</persName> under the guidance of <persName>Aida-Hamed</persName>2. We were at the passage relating to the two genuflections in the dawn worship when the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName> arrived.  <persName>Mahmud</persName> also studied part of this book under the direction of <persName>Ahmed-ben-'Otsmân</persName>, but I do not remember with whom he completed the study. He then began to study the <title>Tehdih</title> under his brother.</p>

<p>
<persName><roleName>The jurisconsult</roleName> El-Mokhtàr, <roleName>the grammarian</roleName></persName>, <persName> <persName>Mahmud</persName></persName>'s maternal uncle, also returned to <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>. As for <persName> <persName>Mahmud</persName></persName>'s father, <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>, 'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqit</persName>, he died there (in <placeName>Biro</placeName>).</p>

<p>
When the tyrant had ceased to rule,  <persName>Mahmud</persName>, who lived in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>, wrote to his brother, <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Abdallah, who was then in <placeName>Tâzekhta</placeName>, a town in the neighborhood of <placeName>Biro</placeName>. In this letter he ordered his brother to come to
In this letter he ordered his brother to come to <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>, but the latter answered that he would never come to this city, because the people of Sankoré would not accept him.

<note n="1">This prince bore the title of <placeName>Mossi</placeName>-koï.</note>

<note n="2">The printed text <foreign/>, instead of <foreign/>, the true lesson given by the ms. C.</note>




<pb n="114"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="144"/>
 

took no account of the ties of kinship, nor of filial duties, and poured out slander against one another.
He added that moreover he did not want to live where the posterity of <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> was. Finally, if it was absolutely necessary for him to live in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>, he wanted it not to be anywhere else than in the neighborhood of the great mosque in the vicinity of <persName><roleName>Sultan</roleName> El-Oudjli</persName>, the father of <persName>'Omar-Biro</persName>, because he knew the excellent feelings of this personage because of the good relations they had had together when they were neighbors in Tâzekhou.
neighbors in <placeName>Tâzekhta</placeName>. So he remained in <placeName>Biro</placeName> until his death (God have mercy on him and make us share in his blessings!).</p>

<p>As soon as he was settled in <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>, the father of blessings, <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>  <persName>Mahmud</persName>, assiduously frequented <persName><roleName>the cadi</roleName> Habib</persName> in order to learn from him theology1. This lasted until the day when <persName>Habib</persName>, his master, died and left him (<ref target="70">٧٠</ref>) his duties as <roleName>cadi</roleName> and advising him not to associate with rich people in their homes as soon as he was appointed <roleName>cadi</roleName>. He was only making this recommendation to him to avoid the harm that would result from this association for the weak and unfortunate, for he had been able to judge for himself the disadvantages that this presented.</p>

<p> <persName>Mahmud</persName> complied with the instructions of the deceased (God have mercy on them both and be favorable to us for their sake in this world and the next!)</p>

<p>
Then Prince <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> undertook to dig a canal
from <placeName>Ras-el-ma</placeName> to reach <placeName>Biro</placeName>2 by water. He deployed for this work all his efforts and was spending the greatest activity on it, when the news came to him

<note n="1">Or <gloss>science</gloss> in a general way. However, it is more likely that the word <foreign xml:lang="ara">علم</foreign> here is used to refer to theology.</note>

<note n="2">This canal was not intended to favor the commerce of this city, but
to make it easier to attack.</note>
<pb n="115"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="145"/>
 
that the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName> had decided to march against him at the head of his troops and attack him. The place where <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> was when he received this news is called <placeName>Chan-Fenech</placeName>1 and that is where the canal stopped. Thus God spared the people of <placeName>Biro</placeName> from the misfortune that threatened them.2 </p>

<p>Then going to meet the king of the <placeName>Mossi</placeName>, <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> made contact with him at <placeName>Djiniki-To'oï</placeName>, a town near the city of <placeName>Kobi</placeName> behind the River. The battle took place there and <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>, victorious, put the king of <placeName>Mossi</placeName> to flight and pursued him to the limit of his states, into whose territory he entered. This battle took place in the year 888 (1483).</p>

<p>
<persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> then retraced his steps; he camped at <placeName>Dira</placeName>, and then set out to conquer the mountains, as previously stated. After that he made an expedition against  <placeName>Gourma</placeName>, was victorious and sacked the country.
This was his last expedition. On leaving <placeName>Batira</placeName>, he had the rampart of <placeName>Kabara</placeName> called <placeName>Tila</placeName> restored, in the year 890
(1485).</p>

<p>
In that year, <persName>El-Hâdj-Ahmed-ben-'Omar-ben-Mohammed-Aqît</persName> went to the East to make the pilgrimage to <placeName>Mecca</placeName> and he returned at the time of the violence of the Kharedjite <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>, according to what <persName>Ahmed-Baba</persName> reports, in the Dzeil.
In 891 (1486), the <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName>-Koi, El-Mokhtàr-ben-Mohammed-Naddi, was arrested and put in prison by order of Sonni-Ali. The following year, in 892 (1487), in the presence of <persName><roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName> Abd-el Djebbâr-Koko</persName>, the name of <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> was pronounced in <placeName>Arafa</placeName>3 and <persName>Abd-el-Djebbâr</persName> made imprecations against him. From that moment the power of the prince decayed and soon came to an end.</p>

<note n="1">Or: Chan-Fenes.</note>

<note n="2">That is, the execution of the channel.</note>

<note n="3">Hill in <placeName>Mecca</placeName> where certain ceremonies of the pilgrimage are performed.</note>
<pb n="116"/>
<milestone unit="scannumber" n="146"/>


<p>The <roleName>Tosoko</roleName>1 affair took place in 893 (1488). It was during this year that the people of <placeName>Timbuktu</placeName> entered
<placeName>Hauki</placeName> where they remained for five years. Among the people who emigrated at that time were: <persName><roleName>the saint of God</roleName>, Sidi Aboul-Qâsem-Et-Touâti</persName>; the father of blessings, <roleName>the jurisconsult</roleName>  <persName>Mahmud</persName>, his brother El-Hâdj-Ahmed, etc. (God have mercy on them!).
Moaddib-Zonkâsi died in 894 (1489) (<ref target="arpage71">٧١</ref>) and, in 898
(1492-93) <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName>, son of  <persName>Sonni-Mahmud-Da'ou</persName>, died on his way back from his expedition to <placeName>Gourma</placeName>, where he had fought against <rs type="ethnic">the Zeghrâni</rs> and <rs type="ethnic">the Foulâni</rs>. When he arrived in the country of <placeName>Gourma</placeName>, at the moment of his return, he was carried away by a torrent called <placeName>Koni</placeName> and perished by the will of the Mighty, the Almighty, on the 15th of the month of moharrem, the first of the months of the year 898 (November 6, 1492) of the hegira. His children cut open his belly, took out the entrails and filled the cavity with honey so that the body would not be corrupted. But it is claimed that God did this to him2 as a punishment for his life-long tyranny over the people. The army of <persName>Sonni-'Ali</persName> camped at <placeName>Ba'anayiya</placeName>.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>